<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Justification evangelical, or, A plain impartial scripture-account of God's method in justifying a sinner written by Sir Charles Wolseley ...</title>
            <author>Wolseley, Charles, Sir, 1630?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15406</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12597015</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12597015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66871)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 971:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Justification evangelical, or, A plain impartial scripture-account of God's method in justifying a sinner written by Sir Charles Wolseley ...</title>
                  <author>Wolseley, Charles, Sir, 1630?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 133 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Ponder ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [10]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Justification.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:64072:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64072:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64072:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. London.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64072:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtification Evangelical:</hi> Or a Plain Impartial SCRIPTURE-Account OF GOD's Method in Juſtifying a SINNER.</p>
            <p>Written by Sir <hi>CHARLES WOLSELEY,</hi> Bart.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea 14.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Who is wiſe, and he ſhall underſtand theſe things? prudent, and he ſhall know them? for the ways of the Lord are right, and the juſt ſhall walk in them: but the tranſgreſſors ſhall fall therein.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Ponder,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in the <hi>Poultry</hi> near <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and in <hi>Chancery-lane</hi> near <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64072:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64072:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoever Treats upon this Weighty and moſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Subject of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ought to do it with great Caution, with great Humility, and with great Sincerity. Firſt, with great Caution, for 'tis
<pb facs="tcp:64072:4"/>a point, about which, not only the beſt Learn'd, but the moſt Holy and moſt Sincerely Religious have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably differ'd, and in all ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts both Grace and Diſcretion will inſtruct a man not to ruſh in violently, or ſuddenly to declare againſt any one ſide; or yet eaſily to ſuppoſe the truth wholly appropriated to any one party: But in every advance to proceed with Moderation and Circumſpection. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, with great Humility,
'tis not a ſit Subject for Proud and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull Pens; the thing in its own nature is of a ſtupendious and humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Conſideration, and ought to be diſcourſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of accordingly; that an Apoſtate creature in open Rebellion against the Great God, ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:64072:4"/>be forgiven by an Act of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty; but that it ſhould become a righteous thing with God to forgive him, and that he ſhould be Juſtified in his ſight, be brought to ſtand <hi>rectus in curia</hi> before his Tribunal, and at the Bar of his infinite Juſtice, and his diſcharge be an Act Judicial, and as much the effect of Juſtice as Favour, is that which nothing leſs then Divine Wiſdom could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived or effected, and when we duely reflect upon it, we find no leſs cauſe for mortifying Adoration, then humble Thanksgiving, and Infinite for both. Thirdly, with great Integrity, the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream intereſt of mankind (their Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal condition hereafter) is ſo bound up herein, and the true notion of this point
<pb facs="tcp:64072:5"/>ſo inſeperably neceſſary to it, that as men regard the ſouls of others, or have any value for their own; they ought with the utmoſt Sincerity, when they diſcuſs this point to deſign themſelves intirely to the ſervice of Truth, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off all Byaſs of Intereſt and Party; and all reſpect to the Pleaſures of men, Alone endeavour to arrive at a cleer and full Diſcovery of what God has reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us in his Word about this matter: Theſe Rules I propoſed to my ſelf when I firſt engaged in theſte Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and I hope the Reader will find nothing in the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that will occaſion him to think I have wilfully tranſgreſſed any of them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64072:5"/>
            <p>Many Books I know there are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant upon this Subject, but to deal freely with my Reader, the conſideration thereof has been ſo far from diverting the publication of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that it has rather been the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it: 'Tis apparent to all that are converſant herein, how greatly this point has been obſcur'd by multitude of words; and I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dared that many who want leaſure, or Inclination, or happily Ability to travail far into Polemick Intricacies, will yet think an hour or two not ill ſpent to read over a plain ſhort Scripture account of this matter.</p>
            <p>I will no farther attempt to pre-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my Reader, but only to aſſure
<pb facs="tcp:64072:6"/>him I have omitted no neceſſary dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that I thought might capacitate me for this ſervice: I have carefully and Impartially peruſed what the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Doctors have urg'd in defence of their Doctrine, and with what Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I could, have conſidered over all the eminent Proteſtant Writers upon this Subject; and although I highly value the Works of many of theſe latter both Dead and yet living, and have learn't much from them, yet I have purpoſely forborn to mention their Names for the ſame reaſon I find given by <hi>Grotius,</hi> in the Preface to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Annotations upon the Goſpels: <hi>Peperci autem plerumque recitandis nominibus quod ea videam factioſo hoc ſaeculo magis ad oblimandum
<pb facs="tcp:64072:6"/>quam ad defaecandum judicium va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should this endeavour ſucceed ſo well as to inform any that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ignorant of this moſt eſſential part of Divinity, or to unite any good men who have differently conceived hereof, it will turn much to my ſatisfaction; if any that are Judicious and Learned ſhall expreſs their diſlike of any part of this Diſcourſe, I ſhall upon all occaſions endeavour by a juſt defence to render it more acceptable to them; but if I find my ſelf at any time attack'd by ſuch as delight in Contention, and love to turn all Polemick Diſcourſes into impertinent Squabble. I reſolve not to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by them, nor upon any terms be brought (to uſe the modern Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb facs="tcp:64072:7"/>
               <hi>ſerram reciprocare;</hi> and indeed to all that ſort of men, that ſullen anſwer before-hand, may be proper enough and ſufficient: <hi>What I have Written, I have Written.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA'S</head>
            <p>PAge 11 line 21 for <hi>By that</hi> read <hi>By Chriſt,</hi> p. 15 l. 27 for <hi>prevailing</hi> r. <hi>Prevalency,</hi> p. 29 l. 6. after <hi>were</hi> add <hi>not,</hi> p. 32 l. 19. after <hi>were</hi> add <hi>in,</hi> p. 48 l. 25 after <hi>ſaw</hi> add <hi>ſit,</hi> p. 51 l. 26 after <hi>that</hi> add <hi>be,</hi> p. 52 l. 28 after <hi>high</hi> add <hi>what,</hi> p. 54 l. 4 for <hi>require</hi> r. <hi>repaired</hi> p. 58 l. 9 after <hi>Believer</hi> add <hi>of,</hi> p. 71 l. 23 for <hi>diſobedience</hi> r. <hi>obedience,</hi> p. 79 l. 16 after <hi>mentions</hi> add <hi>were,</hi> p. 82 l. 23 after <hi>each</hi> add <hi>other,</hi> p. 86 l. 22. after <hi>truth</hi> add <hi>of,</hi> p. 86 l. 23 for <hi>imployes</hi> r. <hi>implyes,</hi> p. 87 l. 2 after <hi>works</hi> add <hi>as,</hi> p. 90 l. 28 for <hi>an</hi> r. <hi>any,</hi> p. 99 l. 24 for <hi>principle</hi> r. <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal,</hi> p. 101 l. 12 after <hi>grace</hi> add <hi>the,</hi> p. 104 l. 8 for <hi>pregnant</hi> r. <hi>regnant,</hi> p. 107 l. 19 after <hi>go</hi> ad <hi>no,</hi> p. 109 l. 9 for <hi>carefully</hi> r. <hi>fully,</hi> p. 116 l. 26 for <hi>ake</hi> r. <hi>make,</hi> p. 121 l. 10 after <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> add <hi>imputed,</hi> p. 129 l. 27 for <hi>men</hi> r. <hi>man.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64072:7"/>
            <head>JUSTIFICATION Evangelical.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N diſcourſing the point of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> theſe three things ſhall be firſt and chiefly conſidered. Firſt; <hi>What is meant in Scripture by</hi> Juſtification. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>What is the material procuring Cauſe of</hi> Juſtification <hi>before God.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>How do we come to partake of the benefits of</hi> Juſtification, <hi>and arrive at a Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to obſcure the meaning of the word <hi>Juſtification</hi> by nice Diſtinctions, and hard and troubleſom Terms: The word <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> comes immediately from the Latine <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificare,</hi> which is not a word of Ancient uſe amongſt the beſt Latine Writers, but is of a Later Edition; has been introduced ſince by Divines, to expreſs the ſenſe of the Greek Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo often uſed by the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint in the Old Teſtament in rendering the Hebrew Verb <hi>Hitzdik,</hi> and ſo often in the New Teſtament, eſpecially by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64072:8"/>meaning of it, is, to <hi>Juſtify,</hi> and make, <hi>Juſt</hi> by way of <hi>Vindication, Defence</hi> or in <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Not by <hi>infuſing a habit,</hi> for it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that both the Hebrew and the Greek Verbs, (from whence we muſt fetch the true ſenſe of the Latin and Engliſh,) are <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial</hi> and <hi>Forinſical</hi> words, and arc ſcarce ever taken throughout the Bible to <hi>Juſlify,</hi> by <hi>making inherently Juſt,</hi> or <hi>Juſt</hi> by <hi>Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</hi> The natural and primitive ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them both, is, to juſtifie <hi>Legally</hi> and <hi>Judicially,</hi> to make juſt by <hi>Plea,</hi> and in <hi>Judgement.</hi> And in that original ſenſe, or in a ſenſe relative to it, and derivative from it, are the words generally taken in <hi>Scripture.</hi> When either <hi>God is ſaid to Juſtifie man,</hi> or <hi>man is ſaid to juſtifie God,</hi> or <hi>one man is ſaid to juſtifie another,</hi> or <hi>one and the ſame man to juſtifie himſelf,</hi> (for all theſe wayes we read of <hi>Juſtification</hi> in Scripture) 'tis ſtill without any ſignification of <hi>infuſing</hi> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or making <hi>juſt</hi> that way: But that which is intended by the word, is, to make <hi>juſt defenſatively, declaratively, judicially,</hi> and not <hi>qualitively.</hi> To give some inſtance of many, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Not the hearers of the Law but the doers of it,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>shall be juſtified;</hi> That is, pronounced and declared <hi>Juſt</hi> in judgment. In the 11 Chap. of <hi>Job</hi> v. 2. <hi>Should a man full of talk be juſtified?</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64072:8"/>that is, ſhould he be <hi>defended</hi> and <hi>acquitted</hi> upon that account, becauſe he is full of words? Shall that be a ſufficient Plea for him? So when we are told <hi>Pro.</hi> 17. v. 15. that, <hi>To juſtifie the wicked is an abomination to the Lord,</hi> 'tis meant to juſtifie them by <hi>pleading</hi> for them, and <hi>defending</hi> them, or to <hi>juſtifie</hi> them in <hi>judgment,</hi> while wicked. For, to <hi>juſtifie</hi> them in the other ſenſe, to make them <hi>inherently juſt</hi> and <hi>righteous,</hi> is no <hi>abomination to the Lord,</hi> but a thing he has every where declared himſelf to be well pleaſed with. In the 8 of the <hi>Rom.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> puts this queſtion, <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect?</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>It is God that juſtifieth:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Who shall condemn?</hi> where, by Gods <hi>juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> is meant, his <hi>acquitting</hi> and <hi>clearing</hi> in <hi>judgment;</hi> 'Tis evident to be such a <hi>juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> as ſtands in oppoſition to <hi>charging</hi> and <hi>condemning.</hi> Of the ſame import are the words moſt generally whereſoever we find them uſed by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> either in the Old or New Teſtament. And this we have acknowledged by many of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> on the one hand, and some of the <hi>Socinians</hi> on the other, though both of them endeavour to prove that Gods <hi>juſtifying</hi> men, is not his <hi>pronouncing</hi> them <hi>juſt,</hi> and his <hi>declaring</hi> them so in a <hi>judicial</hi> way, but his <hi>infuſing</hi> of <hi>habits</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64072:9"/>and making them in themſelves <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>habitually righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtification</hi> in general may be conſidered as it may relate to two ſorts of men: Firſt, to <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>innocent</hi> men, and Secondly to <hi>Offenders. Juſtification</hi> in both caſes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth <hi>Charge,</hi> and <hi>Accuſation,</hi> and ſtands in oppoſition to <hi>Condemnation.</hi> A Righteous perſon when he is accuſed and found fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that is, inherently Righteous, and Juſt, he is, by his righteouſneſs made evident, thereby <hi>juſtified,</hi> that is, <hi>declared</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> to be <hi>juſt,</hi> acquitted and cleared both from <hi>accuſation</hi> and <hi>condemnation. David</hi> hath an expreſſion to this purpoſe of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> the 51. <hi>That thou mighteſt be juſtified when thou ſpeakeſt:</hi> That is, be <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> by being manifeſted to be really <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>juſt.</hi> So Good men are ſometimes ſaid to be <hi>juſtified</hi> by their <hi>works,</hi> that is, <hi>defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and vindicated againſt <hi>falſe accuſation</hi> and <hi>charge,</hi> approved and declared to be <hi>juſt</hi> thereby. A perſon ſo qualified, is <hi>juſtified,</hi> becauſe he appears to be in himſelf <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>juſt,</hi> not <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>juſt</hi> becauſe <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> Secondly, an <hi>Offender</hi> when he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, he can be no other way <hi>juſtified,</hi> that is, <hi>defended</hi> againſt <hi>accuſation,</hi> and <hi>acquitted</hi> in judgment, but by pleading ample and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> made for an <hi>offence,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64072:9"/>and an <hi>acceptance</hi> of that ſatisfaction as ſuch, and procuring a <hi>remiſſion</hi> of the <hi>offence</hi> thereupon. 'Tis not poſſible to contrive any other way of <hi>Juſtification</hi> in that Caſe; For <hi>free</hi> and <hi>abſolute</hi> remiſſion of an offence can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be called <hi>Juſtification.</hi> The more freely a man is pardoned without any <hi>ſort</hi> of <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> the leſs he can be properly ſaid to be <hi>juſtified.</hi> Such a man now is not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, becauſe he is found to be <hi>inherently juſt,</hi> and without <hi>fault,</hi> but he becomes Juſt, is brought into the ſtate of a <hi>juſt</hi> man, becauſe he arrives at a <hi>Legal Juſtification,</hi> and upon <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> made, obtains an <hi>acquitment</hi> in <hi>judgment. Juſtification</hi> in ſcripture, as 'tis an act of God relating to Men, is ever ſpoken of in this later way. 'Tis never meant to excuſe or juſtifie a Sinner <hi>from</hi> being a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> but to juſtifie a ſinner, ſuppoſing him a <hi>ſinner</hi> to the <hi>utmoſt:</hi> All <hi>Goſpel-juſtification</hi> being founded upon <hi>Satisfaction</hi> as the grand fundamental of it.</p>
            <p>But to come more nearly to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-ſenſe, and meaning of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> by which we are generally told, that all Sinners unpardoned are under <hi>Divine Wrath,</hi> and ſtand <hi>Condemned</hi> at Gods <hi>Bar:</hi> and that ſuch whom God is pleaſed in the method of his Grace judicially to pardon, and receive into favour, he is thereby ſaid to <hi>juſtifie.</hi> To be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64072:10"/>
               <hi>justified</hi> therefore in Scripture ſenſee, is, <hi>to be Cleared and Diſcharged before the Tribunal of God from the Guilt of ſin, reſulting from the breach of his Laws, and Abſolved from the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due from Divine Justice thereunto.</hi> This, without any obſcuring Speculation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the nature of <hi>Justification</hi> in general, is that practical account we find the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to give us of it ſuitable to its nature, as it relates to <hi>ſinful offending Man,</hi> (for it muſt ſtill be remembred, that Gods <hi>justifying</hi> in Scripture, is, <hi>his giving ſentence with the Guilty party,</hi> and ſo we can only be <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> becauſe <hi>juſtified,</hi> and <hi>justified</hi> by being <hi>pardoned,</hi>) and according to what it <hi>Operates</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> upon the ſubject, by which alſo 'tis beſt underſtood, and becomes moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to every Capacity. I include not herein the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> nor the <hi>Condition</hi> of it, but ſpeak of it in its own proper <hi>form,</hi> and <hi>ſimply</hi> in it ſelf conſidered: For, had I ſo done, I would after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner have expreſſed my ſelf. <hi>Justification is an act of God whereby he does, for the ſake of Chriſts Satisfaction to his Justice; upon mens ſincere Beliefe of the Goſpel, account their faith for righteouſneſs, pardon their ſins, and Acquit them in Judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this Deſcription I have given of <hi>Justification,</hi> and our being <hi>justified,</hi> is that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64072:10"/>which ought to be given, and the direct ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count we have of it in Scripture, will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear from theſe four conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Fiſt, Sin being a <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> of Gods <hi>Law,</hi> and ſo an <hi>Offence</hi> accountable for to <hi>Him,</hi> nothing <hi>leſs</hi> can <hi>justify</hi> a ſinner then the <hi>Supream judgement of God Himſelf,</hi> as the <hi>Soveraign Lord</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> of all the Earth. The <hi>Apostle</hi> tells us that in few words, <hi>It is God that justifies.</hi> And He does it as an act and exerciſe of his <hi>Supream Justice;</hi> according to that paſſage <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. v. 26. <hi>That God might be just, and the iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of him that believeth in Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Gods <hi>justifying</hi> men, ſtands in oppoſition to <hi>Accuſation</hi> and <hi>Condemnation,</hi> which we have plainly expreſſed in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned 8th. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> where the Apoſtle oppoſeth Gods <hi>justifying,</hi> to <hi>Charging</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning. Who ſhall lay any thing to the Charge of Gods elect? It is God that justifieth, Who is he that condemneth?</hi> So that if you know what it is to <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Condemn,</hi> you will know what it is to <hi>juſtifie,</hi> it being natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evidenced by its Contraries. And as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> is the reſult of a <hi>Law,</hi> ſo is <hi>Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> We ſtand <hi>Condemned</hi> by the <hi>Law</hi> of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64072:11"/>
               <hi>works,</hi> and are <hi>justified</hi> by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>faith.</hi> Now, what is it that Mankind is publickly <hi>accuſed of,</hi> and <hi>charged</hi> with in Scripture? 'Tis <hi>Sin.</hi> What is it that men ſtand <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> for at Gods Bar? 'Tis <hi>Sin.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>Justification</hi> muſt needs be a <hi>Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Diſcharging</hi> ſome way or other from it. And that which the Scripture every where intends by <hi>Justification,</hi> is the <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and Gods <hi>acquitting</hi> us in Judgment from the <hi>Charge, Guilt, Condemna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of it. This is judiciouſly obſerved by <hi>Grotius, Justificatio ut notum eſt paſſim in ſacris literis ſed maxime in Paulinis Epiſtolis, Abſolutionem ſignificat, quae preſuppoſito peccat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſiſtit in pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum remiſſione, ipſo Paul ſemet clare expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cante pr ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtim, Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Pe Satiſ. Chriſ chap.</hi> 1. <hi>pa</hi> 38. And this I ſhall endeavour to prove theſe ſeveral wayes. Firſt, by producing divers Texts, wherein the <hi>Foly Ghoſt</hi> ſpeaks ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> of ſin in the Goſpel way, as one and the <hi>ſame</hi> thing. Secondly, by ſhewing that the whole <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> of that <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> upon which (as the Ground of it) we are <hi>justified,</hi> is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally iſſued in Scripture into the <hi>Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſin.</hi> Thirdly, by ſhewing that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>other expreſſions</hi> the Scripture at any time makes uſe of to ſignifie and Explain Juſtification to us by, they all tend to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64072:11"/>give us this <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>ſignification</hi> of it, and to expreſs it to us as conſiſting in the <hi>forgiveneſs of ſin.</hi> And fourthly, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the <hi>Grand Bleſſing</hi> that God ſtill promiſed the world ſhould partake of by the <hi>Covenant</hi> to his <hi>Grace,</hi> and the ſending of his <hi>Son,</hi> (from whence our <hi>Juſtification</hi> has its riſe,) was the <hi>Pardon</hi> and <hi>forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſin.</hi> And when I have done this, there will be no need I hope to ſay more for the ſatisfaction of any, under this <hi>Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt. In the 4. <hi>chap.</hi> to the <hi>Rom.</hi> where St <hi>Paul</hi> treats more fully and more Critically of Juſtification then he does in any other place, he there deſcribes it in a Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation out of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> by the <hi>forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſin,</hi> and the <hi>non imputation of iniquity. But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs: Even as</hi> David <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the bleſſedneſs of the man unto whom God imputeth righteouſneſs without works, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and whoſe ſin is covered: Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute iniquity. Cometh this bleſſedneſs then upon the circumciſion only, or upon the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion alſo?</hi> Where 'tis not to be fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed, but that he deſcribes the <hi>bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64072:12"/>of a <hi>Juſtified</hi> perſon by the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> of a <hi>Pardoned</hi> perſon, as being <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame.</hi> In the 9 <hi>ver. Cometh this bleſſedneſs</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>upon the Circumciſion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or upon the uncircumciſion alſo?</hi> What <hi>bleſſedneſs?</hi> Why, the Bleſſedneſs he is treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, the Bleſſedneſs of being <hi>juſtified</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: which he proves, deſcends both upon <hi>Jew and Gentile</hi> in the Goſpel way of <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>believing.</hi> And what is that <hi>bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of being juſtified before <hi>God?</hi> Wherein lyes it? Why, 'tis the Bleſſedneſs he tells us that <hi>David deſcribes, of having our iniquities forgiven, and our ſins covered,</hi> the Bleſſedneſs of <hi>having God not to impute ſin to us.</hi> 'Tis plain, the Apoſtles whole ſcope and drift, is, to prove that <hi>Abrahams juſtification</hi> was his <hi>pardon;</hi> upon which acccount the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> though great ſinners, might be <hi>juſtified,</hi> as well as he: and <hi>that Juſtification before God, is not by works,</hi> and ſo <hi>not from the merit of any inherent righteouſneſs of our own,</hi> but by Gods gracious <hi>Imputing righteouſneſs without works,</hi> which he makes to conſiſt in <hi>the Pardon of ſin, and Not imputing of iniquity,</hi> and to be the ſame thing with it. In the 13th. of the <hi>Acts</hi> the 38 and 39 verſes, we find the Apoſtle again expreſſing himſelf to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Be it known unto you therefore men and brethren, that through this man is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64072:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>preached unto you the forgiveneſs of ſins, And by him all that believe are juſtified from all things, from which they could not be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law of</hi> Moſes. Where he ſpeaks of <hi>remiſſion of ſins,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently,</hi> as terms importing the <hi>ſame thing.</hi> In the 18th. of <hi>Luke,</hi> where the <hi>Publican</hi> is ſaid to <hi>ſmite upon his breaſt,</hi> and ſeek for <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>forgiveneſs,</hi> in that expreſſion, <hi>God be merciful to me a ſinner;</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſays, <hi>He went home to his houſe Justified,</hi> (that is, <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned) rather then the proud Phariſee.</hi> The one <hi>juſtified himſelf,</hi> and asked <hi>no forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the other <hi>condemned himſelf,</hi> and ſought for the <hi>pardon</hi> of his ſins: And by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours own determination, took the right method of attaining <hi>Juſtification</hi> thereby. In the 5th of the <hi>Rom.</hi> v. 16. The Apoſtle treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the difference between <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, and the condemnation introduced thereby, and the Salvation we have by that, tells us, <hi>And not as it was by one that ſinned, ſo is the gift, for the judgement was by one to condemnation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>but the free gift, is, of many offences unto juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> By the free gift of many <hi>offences,</hi> is meant the <hi>pardon</hi> of them, and the <hi>pardon</hi> of them is unto <hi>Justification,</hi> that is, <hi>pardon</hi> of ſin amounts to <hi>Justification,</hi> and upon <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> we are actually <hi>juſtified.</hi> We are often
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64072:13"/>ſaid in Scripture to have <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>remiſſion of ſins by Chriſts blood:</hi> And in the 5th. of the <hi>Rom.</hi> and the 9 <hi>verſ.</hi> we are there ſaid to be <hi>juſtified by his blood: Much more now being juſtified by his blood, ſhall we be ſaved from wrath through him.</hi> By all which we are told, that the ſcripture generally intends by <hi>justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> and <hi>pardon,</hi> one and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The whole <hi>advantage</hi> and <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> of that <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> upon which we come to be <hi>juſtified</hi> before God, is often iſſued into the <hi>pardon of ſin,</hi> and by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture comprized therein. If we look to the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Prefigurations</hi> of that ſatisfaction under the Law, the grand <hi>end</hi> and <hi>ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of them, was the <hi>removing</hi> and <hi>purging of ſin.</hi> This the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Without ſhedding of blood is no remiſſion.</hi> And in the 26 <hi>ver.</hi> (he ſayes,) <hi>Chriſt had once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the end of the world to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf.</hi> That was the grand thing typified and intended by the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> to be done, and that which our Saviour by his coming actually did do, as we are told in the 1ſt. <hi>chap.</hi> of the ſame book, in that expreſſion, <hi>When he had by himſelf purged our ſins, he ſate down on the right hand of the Majesty on high.</hi> That is, When he had fully accompliſhed that great End for which he came into the world, which was to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64072:13"/>procure <hi>pardon</hi> of ſins, he then aſcended to his Mediatory Throne, and the exerciſe of that Authority. If we look into the Goſpel, in the 26 of St. <hi>Matt.</hi> where our bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> firſt inſtituted, and ſolemnly himſelf ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred that <hi>Sacrament,</hi> wherein Himſelf, and all the ſaving Advantages appurtenant to him, are repreſented, and conveyed, He there calls his Blood <hi>the blood of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Declaring that to be the grand Effect of his purchaſe, and the great attainment of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, from whence all our happineſs is derived. In the 1ſt. of the <hi>Epheſ v.</hi> 7. the Redemption we have by Chriſt, is called the <hi>forgiveneſs of ſin: In whom we have redemption through his blood the forgiveneſs of ſins.</hi> In the 2d. of the <hi>Acts verſ.</hi> 38. St. <hi>Peter</hi> there perſwades the <hi>Jews</hi> to embrace the <hi>Chriſtian-religion</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Repent and be baptized for the remiſſion of ſins,</hi> as the great End attainable by the Goſpel and all the Inſtitutions of it. St. <hi>John</hi> in the 1ſt. <hi>chap.</hi> of his 1ſt. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> tells us that, <hi>If we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son Cleanſeth us from all ſin:</hi> That being the great End of all Goſpel faith and obedience (to be <hi>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from all ſin</hi>) and the in-let to all happineſs. And 'tis that which all the Saints, the whole
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64072:14"/>Church unitedly do, <hi>una voce,</hi> adore the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator for, as the grand Effect of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, <hi>That he has waſhed them from their ſins in his own blood,</hi> and thereby <hi>made them Kings and Prieſts unto God,</hi> and intituled them to all happineſs, and Glory. In a word, our Saviour himſelf ſumms up and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomizeth all thoſe bleſſings he came to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe for, and confer upon the world, and ſeems to be in the Supreameſt exerciſe of his Mediatory Authority, in pronouncing that Benediction, <hi>Thy ſins are forgiven thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whatever other expreſſions the Scripture makes uſe of to ſignifie and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Juſtification</hi> to us by, they all relate to the <hi>pardon</hi> of ſin, and give us this ſenſe and ſignification of it. The Scripture expreſſeth our <hi>Juſtification</hi> by three other Terms; Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times 'tis called <hi>Redemption,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Reconciliation:</hi> And all theſe have a reference to <hi>ſin</hi> and its <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs.</hi> 'Tis called <hi>Redemption</hi> with reſpect to that <hi>captivity</hi> and <hi>bondage</hi> that is in ſin. <hi>Remiſſion,</hi> with reſpect to that <hi>guilt</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to <hi>puniſhment</hi> that is in ſin. And 'tis called <hi>Reconciliation</hi> with reſpect to that <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> and <hi>oppoſition to</hi> God that is in ſin. All which we are freed from by the <hi>pardon of ſin,</hi> as the great priviledge of a <hi>juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> ſtate, and that wherein it conſiſteth.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64072:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Fourthly, The great <hi>Bleſſing</hi> that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture foretold, and held forth to the world in the coming of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, that God would graciouſly enter into with Mankind, was the <hi>Remiſſion of ſin, and blotting out of iniquity.</hi> Inſtances of this kind the Scripture abounds with. The great effect of Chriſts coming, we are told, ſhould be, <hi>To ſave his people from their ſins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity:</hi> And in divers of the <hi>Prophets</hi> God declares the Grace of his <hi>Covenant</hi> to lye <hi>per eminentiam</hi> in this, <hi>The pardoning of our iniquities, and the remembring our ſins no more.</hi> So St. <hi>Peter</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>To</hi> Him <hi>give all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets witneſs, that thorough his name whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever believeth in him ſhall receive Remiſſion of ſins.</hi> And when God was pleaſed to make the Attributes of his Mercy and Goodneſs in an eſpecial manner to paſs before <hi>Moſes,</hi> and to reveal it to him, as it relates to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, 'tis expreſſed by That, as the Grand and Tranſcendent Effect of it, <hi>the pardoning iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third conſideration to clear up the truth of this Definition I have given of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> (and which is of great prevailing in the caſe) is this; That whenever God pardons any mans ſin, He looks upon him as a <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64072:15"/>perſon,</hi> does <hi>cerſtitute</hi> him ſo thereby, and <hi>deal</hi> with him accordingly. Where he <hi>ſees no iniquity,</hi> there his Countenance is as upon the <hi>righteous.</hi> This I ſhall make out. Firſt, from the Reaſons of the Thing in it ſelf abſtractedly conſidered, that it ought ſo to be. Secondly from plain and poſitive Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the caſe, whereby it appears to be Gods ordination that ſo it ſhould be. And thirdly, from the Method God is pleaſed in his wiſdom to take in the pardoning and juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Offenders, and the manner of his proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure therein, whereby his Righteouſneſs and his Juſtice become very evident in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>There be theſe five Reaſons reſult from the Thing in it ſelf abſtractedly conſidered for the proof of this point. Firſt, Man in his primary Make, was <hi>righteous,</hi> and <hi>juſt,</hi> that was his Original conſtitution; Sin is but an Accidental Deprivation: And therefore when all Sin and Guilt contracted, is Legally <hi>removed,</hi> and wholly <hi>obliterated,</hi> 'tis but reaſonable he ſhould be judg d of by his <hi>firſt ſtate,</hi> and it falls in naturally ſo to be. <hi>Sublata privatione ponitur habitus,</hi> is a firm Axiom in Logick. Not that I am here about to prove that a man is reſtored <hi>barely</hi> to the ſtate of <hi>Adams Original innocency</hi> by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Forgiveneſs of the Goſpel, for by Gods gracious Ordination we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64072:15"/>in <hi>much more;</hi> I urge this only to evidence thus much, That man being made Righteous, and having made himſelf a Sinner, his ſin being pardoned and obliterated, were there nothing elſe in the caſe, 'twere Juſt with God to account of him according to what at firſt he <hi>made</hi> him. Nor can we, with any good Reaſon, abſtractedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering him ſo circumſtanced, judge of him otherwiſe, then as in a <hi>righteous,</hi> and ſo <hi>happy</hi> condition. Secondly, Remiſſion of all ſin is in its own nature conſtructively, and properly enough ſo called, a <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> According to that noted ſaying among the Antient Chriſtians, <hi>Hominis juſticia eſt Dei Indulgentia;</hi> He that is chargeable with <hi>no offence</hi> at Gods Tribunal, as he is not that has all his ſins both of omiſſion and commiſſion judicially and authoritatively for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, muſt needs be Reputed upon <hi>even terms</hi> with an <hi>Obſerver of the whole Law,</hi> and have a <hi>right</hi> to all the <hi>advantages</hi> appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to an <hi>innocent perſon.</hi> To want any of them were <hi>paena damni,</hi> and a part of <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi> which can have no place where there is no Sin nor Tranſgreſſion. Thirdly, Man is a Subject in which <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>unrighteouſneſs</hi> do neceſſarily <hi>inhere,</hi> and to which by virtue of his Conſtitution and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation they are inſeparably appertaining:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64072:16"/>Juſt as <hi>light</hi> and <hi>darkneſs</hi> neceſſarily relate to <hi>Aire, health</hi> and <hi>ſickneſs</hi> to our <hi>bodyes:</hi> And they are <hi>contraryes</hi> that <hi>expel</hi> each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from a <hi>neceſſity</hi> in their own <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſucceed</hi> each other in their Exiſtance in ſuch Subjects. <hi>Air</hi> perfectly free from all <hi>darkneſs,</hi> muſt of neceſſity be ſuppoſed to be <hi>light.</hi> If a <hi>body</hi> be free from all ſort of <hi>ſickneſs,</hi> it muſt needs be ſuppoſed in perfect <hi>health:</hi> So if a <hi>Man</hi> be freed wholly from all ſort of <hi>unrighteouſneſs,</hi> he ought not, nor cannot be otherwiſe judged of then as a <hi>Juſt</hi> and a <hi>Righteous</hi> perſon; there being no <hi>third ſtate</hi> imaginable in ſuch caſes. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, If Gods Pardon of all a mans ſin ſhould not <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> inſtate him in a Righteous condition, and render him perfectly a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon, one of theſe two things would unavoidably inſue; Either that there muſt be ſome <hi>third ſtate</hi> of a man that is neither Righteous nor Unrighteous, which is in the nature of the thing utterly Impoſſible to be, or elſe that God might fully <hi>pardon</hi> an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous man,</hi> that is, a man <hi>after</hi> his <hi>pardon Continuing</hi> ſtill <hi>ſo</hi> to be, and that a man might <hi>remain unrighteous,</hi> and ſo obnoxious to Puniſhment, <hi>miſerable</hi> and <hi>unhappy,</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſo often ſayes, <hi>That he is bleſſed that has his ſins forgiven,</hi>) after all his ſins are Pardoned, and he has
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64072:16"/>reaped the whole benefit of Gods Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: To imagine either of which, were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extreamly Impious, or Fooliſh, or Both. Fifthly, The Apoſtle tells us, that <hi>All un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs</hi> is <hi>ſin,</hi> (the Scripture carryes us no farther) and <hi>all ſin</hi> is ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>a breach and tranſgreſſion of ſome Law.</hi> Now where all ſort of ſin is Forgiven, both of Omiſſion and Commiſſion, a man is in the <hi>ſame ſtate</hi> as if he had <hi>never offended,</hi> and if ſo, capable of <hi>no charge</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> and ſo of <hi>no charge</hi> of <hi>unrighteouſneſs,</hi> and ſo cannot by <hi>ſtrict rules of Juſtice,</hi> be otherwiſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged and accounted of then as a <hi>Righteous perſon.</hi> Freedom from all unrighteouſneſs (which Pardon of all ſin neceſſarily includes) does <hi>ipſo facto</hi> conſtitute a man <hi>Righteous,</hi> and denominate him from the Reaſon of the thing, ſo to be. And the truth is, a perſon whoſe Fault is <hi>remitted,</hi> and he <hi>judicially ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted</hi> upon <hi>plenary ſatisfaction</hi> made, is (in point of true and legal Juſtification, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accounted Righteous thereupon) upon <hi>even termes</hi> with him that is Accuſed, and Juſtifyed by being found <hi>innocent;</hi> Becauſe the Rule of Righteouſneſs and Juſtification is the Law and the Judgement reſulting from thence; Moſt eſpecially when we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted at the <hi>infallible Tribunal</hi> of <hi>God</hi> according to <hi>His righteous Laws.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64072:17"/>Queſtion (ſo pregnant Negative) may very well be asked, <hi>If God juſtify, who ſhall either Charge or Condemn?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It appears by ſeveral Texts, that whomſoever God pardons, he reckons as <hi>Righteous,</hi> and is in the Scripture-acceptation ſaid to <hi>juſtify</hi> thereby. In the 4th. of the <hi>Rom.</hi> where the Apoſtle is proving, that Righteouſneſs and Juſtification is not by <hi>works</hi> and <hi>merit,</hi> but by <hi>free forgiveneſs</hi> in the Goſpel way of Believing: he ſayes in the <hi>6. ver. Even as</hi> David <hi>alſo deſcribeth the bleſſdneſs of the man to whom God imputeth righteouſneſs without works.</hi> Here the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: gives you <hi>Davids ſenſe</hi> in his <hi>own words,</hi> and then quotes <hi>Davids words,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and whoſe ſins are covered, Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute iniquity.</hi> By which it is plain paſt all denyal, that <hi>imputing righteouſneſs without works,</hi> and <hi>free forgiveneſs of ſin,</hi> and <hi>not imputing iniquity,</hi> are the <hi>ſame,</hi> if this be but admitted, <hi>that St.</hi> Paul <hi>know how to interpret the words of</hi> David. In the 2d. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to the <hi>Corinth. chap.</hi> 5th. the Apoſtle there tells us, that <hi>God is in Chriſt reconciling the world unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not imputing their treſpaſſes.</hi> God, upon <hi>not imputing ſin, is reconciled.</hi> Now it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Not imputing ſin, He did not account
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64072:17"/>of us as Righteous, 'twere impoſſible he ſhould be ſo Reconciled: God cannot be <hi>reconciled</hi> to any man <hi>continuing unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and under the notion of a <hi>Sinner.</hi> In truth, Throughout the Scripture, all the <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> of a <hi>righteous</hi> perſon, of a <hi>Happy</hi> and Bleſſed perſon, are ſtill given to a <hi>Pardoned</hi> perſon. As all <hi>miſery</hi> was introduced by <hi>ſin,</hi> to manifeſt Gods extream <hi>hatred</hi> of it. So all <hi>happineſs</hi> is attained by the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs</hi> of it; to tell us of what <hi>value</hi> Gods <hi>forgiveneſs</hi> is , and what an ineſtimable <hi>price</hi> it coſt. In the ſenſe of the Goſpel (which is a Law Enacted that peculiarly provides for the Juſtification of an Offender) a <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> perſon is a <hi>pardoned</hi> perſon, to <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerves. <hi>Cum veniam peccatorum fuerimus conſecuti Juſti habemur coram Deo. Inſtit. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 17. And a <hi>pardoned</hi> perſon is a <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed</hi> perſon, and a <hi>juſtifyed</hi> perſon is bleſſed perſon. <hi>Pardon, Juſtification, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Bleſſedneſs,</hi> are inſeparably Conjoyn'd: The 4th. of the <hi>Rom.</hi> and other Texts are a ſufficient Proof of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, From a due conſideration of that <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Method</hi> God is pleaſed to uſe in the Pardoning of Sinners: 'This truth will be farther manifeſt, and appear to be immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſixed upon theſe two foundations. Firſt, Every ſinner is pardoned upon the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64072:18"/>ſoore of ſuch a Satisfaction made as <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>ſatisfies</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> as much as if it had never been broken; or as if being broken, the <hi>utmoſt penalty</hi> had been inflicted: Now ſuch ſatisfaction is in it ſelf vertually <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> and when <hi>accepted</hi> in <hi>judgement,</hi> is <hi>Actually</hi> ſo. Secondly, Every ſinner is in fact pardoned (and not before) upon the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Condition</hi> as God is pleaſed by the Covenant of his Grace to <hi>account</hi> for <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſo to <hi>accept:</hi> And that is <hi>Believing,</hi> and being poſſeſſed of <hi>Goſpel-faith;</hi> Which Faith we are often told is <hi>imputed for righteouſneſs.</hi> Whoever <hi>believes,</hi> is <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> in the Judgement of the Goſpel-<hi>Law;</hi> for it is performing the condition <hi>required</hi> by it on our part to be performed, and is our Covenant-Keeping. Now, whoſoever is ſo Circumſtanced in a <hi>judicial pardon</hi> obtained from the Great and Infallible Judge of all the Earth, upon ſuch a ſatisfaction made, and ſuch a Condition performed, is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>well intituled</hi> to a <hi>Righteous ſtate</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>A Fourth conſideration to make good the Definition I have given ſhall be this. Gods Juſtifying a ſinner is as has been ſaid, his giving Sentence <hi>with</hi> the <hi>guilty party.</hi> Now God, whoſe Judgement is ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64072:18"/>to Truth, cannot give Sentence <hi>with a Guilty</hi> perſon upon the ſcore of <hi>Innocency;</hi> His Juſtification therefore of ſuch a one, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it which way you will) muſt needs be included in his <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> of him. He muſt of neceſſity be reſtored to a righteous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in a way of <hi>pardon,</hi> and cannot be ſo upon any other account. That which ſome ſay [That Juſtifying, and bare and abſolute Forgiving, are, in themſelves conſidered, two diſtinct things: One being a voluntary act of Grace, the other a neceſſary effect of Juſtice] will not at all reach this caſe, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to be true: For a ſinners Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reſults not from free and abſolute Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, nor conſiſts in it; but a ſinner is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and juſtified in a way <hi>judicial,</hi> in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of a <hi>Law,</hi> by pleading an ample <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction made:</hi> The greateſt exerciſe of <hi>favour</hi> in ſuch a caſe ſeems to lye in the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance</hi> of the ſatisfaction. Now God, who is the Party offended, and the Judge, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring himſelf to be abundantly <hi>ſatisfied</hi> concerning the ſins of the world, by what <hi>Chriſt</hi> has <hi>ſuffered</hi> and <hi>done,</hi> (and it being perhaps highly requiſite, the Nature of Chriſts ſatisfaction conſidered in point of Juſtice too, that he should ſo be) the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Juſtification of a ſinner are eminent effects of his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> as well as of his Grace
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64072:19"/>and Mercy: And it becomes a <hi>Righteous thing now with God to pardon and juſtifie an offender,</hi> ſo qualified <hi>in Judgement.</hi> For, it muſt be conſider'd, that although the Ground and Foundation of our Salvation, and the whole of it in its contriving and effecting, is nothing elſe but <hi>free</hi> and <hi>abſolute grace</hi> and <hi>Divine goodneſs,</hi> yet in ſuch a Method, and after ſuch a Manner is Grace diſpenced, that in every Step that is taken toward the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a ſinner, God appears <hi>Righteous</hi> as well as <hi>Gracious,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy do kiſs each other.</hi> But ſtill the Juſtification of ſuch a one muſt exiſt in his <hi>Pardon,</hi> by which he obtaines a Legal <hi>Diſcharge</hi> from all obligation to Puniſhment, ſtands <hi>rectus in Curia,</hi> no <hi>charge</hi> from the Law can be brought againſt him, and he is upon <hi>even terms</hi> in the eye of the Law, with thoſe who <hi>never offended.</hi> Nor can it be otherwiſe: For no <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> be it never ſo Great, can put an Offender out of <hi>need</hi> of <hi>forgiveneſs,</hi> nor can it operate farther then to <hi>obtain for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs,</hi> and ſo free him from <hi>condemnation,</hi> and conſtitute him <hi>judicially righteous.</hi> 'Tis true, that this is not <hi>ſuch</hi> a Juſtification as an <hi>innocent</hi> perſon obtains in Judgment: But 'tis ſuch a one as an <hi>offender</hi> is only capable of, and has <hi>all</hi> in the <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>advantages</hi> that the other has, and may be as truly and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64072:19"/>properly termed <hi>Juſtification:</hi> And whoever denyes it, makes the <hi>Juſtification</hi> of an <hi>offender</hi> utterly Impracticable, and Impoſſible.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>SECT. II.</head>
            <p>ANd thus I have gone through the firſt Promiſe I obliged my ſelf to, which was, to give an account of what is meant in Scripture by <hi>Juſtification.</hi> We are not Juſtified as <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>innocent</hi> perſons, by having <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſs perſonally imputed to us as our own, and we accounted</hi> in Judgment to have <hi>done</hi> what <hi>He did,</hi> and <hi>acquitted</hi> as <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thereupon:</hi> Such apprehenſions are vain, and have no bottom in Scripture. But we are Juſtified (as in indeed and in truth we are) as <hi>Sinners,</hi> that is, By pleading <hi>ample Satisfaction made for our ſins in Chriſt,</hi> and our <hi>own performance</hi> of that <hi>Goſpel-condition</hi> which God has made neceſſary to our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Benefits of it: Upon which Plea God is graciouſly pleaſed <hi>judicially</hi> to <hi>pardon</hi> our ſins, to account of us as <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> thereupon, and to <hi>deal</hi> with us <hi>according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> that is, Legally to intitle us to all the <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> promiſed in the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:64072:20"/>
            <p>Divers <hi>Objections</hi> are raiſed againſt theſe Conceptions of Juſtification, the value where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſeems to me to reſult rather from the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> of them, (ſundry <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Worthy</hi> men) then from any weight in <hi>themſelves.</hi> The moſt Material are theſe three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is <hi>Objected, That when the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deſcribes Juſtification by Forgiveneſs of ſin, it ſpeaks</hi> Synecdochically, <hi>and expreſſeth the</hi> Whole <hi>by a</hi> Part. <hi>So in the</hi> 4th. <hi>to the</hi> Rom. <hi>and other Texts. And that Text</hi> Rom. 4. v. 25. <hi>is much inſiſted on to prove that Juſtification implyes</hi> more <hi>then Forgivenneſs of ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Objection, it will be acknowledged, can be of no force, unleſs it be proved that the Scripture does in other places aſcribe ſome <hi>other</hi> diſtinct <hi>parts</hi> to Juſtification. There can he but <hi>one</hi> more with any colour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and that is
[Adjudging Righteous upon the ſcore of <hi>ſome righteouſneſs.</hi>] Now it has been before proved, That Pardoning of ſin upon Chriſts <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> contains in it <hi>imputing righteouſneſs without works,</hi> and that in the Apoſtles ſenſe they are all one. When we are told in ſome Texts that we are <hi>juſtified by Chriſt:</hi> in others, That <hi>we obtain forgiveneſs of ſin by Christ:</hi> and in others,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64072:20"/>That <hi>we are made righteous by Chriſt:</hi> By an impartial comparing the Scripture with it ſelt, it appears that <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> thing is intended: For whoever, upon the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Goſpel-condition, is legally Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted in Chriſts ſatisfaction, and thereupon actually Pardoned, is alſo thereby <hi>Juſtified</hi> and adjudged to be <hi>Righteous</hi> by the order and appointment of God in that caſe; and in this the Scripture is every where very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive and plain. That when the Scripture deſcribes Juſtification by Forgiveneſs of ſin, it deſcribes it <hi>Synecdochically,</hi> expreſſing the <hi>whole</hi> by a <hi>part,</hi> there is no good reaſon at all to believe, but quite the contrary, That it deſcribes it <hi>comprehenſively.</hi> For it appears by Scripture-evidence, that the <hi>whole form</hi> of Juſtification is <hi>compriz'd</hi> therein; and the Scripture deſcribes it moſt <hi>generally</hi> by <hi>pardon of ſin,</hi> and moſt <hi>fully</hi> in thoſe places where it treats moſt <hi>largely</hi> and <hi>expreſsly</hi> of it. In the forementioned 4th. <hi>chap.</hi> to the <hi>Rom.</hi> 'twill appear very plain to any impartial Reader, That the Apoſtle there without any <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> deſcribes Juſtification in its <hi>full latitude,</hi> if we conſider theſe things. Firſt, that he there fully and compleatly ſets out the Juſtification of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who in the manner of his Juſtification, was to be the great <hi>pattern</hi> of Juſtification to all ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64072:21"/>ages; and the whole buſineſs of Goſpel-Juſtification was compriz'd in the way and manner of his Juſtification. Secondly, he there ſtates and determines the Grand and Deepeſt point about Juſtification, whether it be by <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>works.</hi> Now if he had not deſcribed it in its <hi>full extent</hi> and <hi>latitude,</hi> and taken in the <hi>whole</hi> of Juſtification in that Quotation out of <hi>David,</hi> by which he proves 'tis not by <hi>works</hi> but by <hi>free forgiveneſs,</hi> his Reaſoning had not been Cogent: For the <hi>Jews</hi> might well have replyed, you ſpeak but of <hi>one part</hi> of Juſtification, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude not about the <hi>whole:</hi> That <hi>part</hi> indeed you prove to conſiſt in the <hi>forgiveneſs of ſin</hi> in the way of <hi>ſaith,</hi> but it appears not but that there may be <hi>other parts alſo</hi> in Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and they may reſult from <hi>works:</hi> And ſo a man may be <hi>in part</hi> juſtified by <hi>free for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>in part</hi> by <hi>works.</hi> Thirdly, the Apoſtle very plainly makes the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> that <hi>David</hi> deſcribes (which in the bleſſedneſs of <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>not imputing ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi>) to be the bleſſedneſs of <hi>Juſtification:</hi> For in the 9th. <hi>ver. Cometh this bleſſedneſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the circumciſion only,</hi> or <hi>upon the uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion alſo?</hi> that is, the bleſſedneſs of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by faith,</hi> which is <hi>Davids bleſſedneſs of pardon.</hi> Now 'twere abſurd to imagine that the Apoſtle ſhould tell us that the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64072:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Juſtification (which muſt needs relate to the whole of it) does conſiſt in <hi>imputing righteouſneſs without works,</hi> which he makes to be all one with the <hi>pardon of ſin, and not imputing iniquity,</hi> unleſs Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were <hi>fully compriz'd therein,</hi> and if it were ſo the <hi>form</hi> of it, that it did as we ſay, <hi>dare eſſe</hi> to it: For nothing elſe can properly contain the Bleſſedneſs of it.</p>
            <p>If it be meant by thoſe that thus Object, That by Pardon of ſin the Scripture does not expreſs the whole <hi>Effects</hi> that accrue by Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: That will be readily granted; for our Pardon and Juſtification is but our <hi>Title in Law</hi> to the Grace and Glory of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, is <hi>not</hi> the very <hi>things themſelves,</hi> though they are all <hi>virtually</hi> contain'd therein, and inſeparably <hi>conjoyned</hi> to it by the inſtitution of God: For, <hi>Whom he juſtifies, them he ſanctifies, and whom he ſanctifies, he glorifies.</hi> And the Apoſtle in the 26 of the <hi>Acts,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes, as inſeparable, <hi>forgiveneſs of ſin, and having an inheritance amongſt them that are ſanctified.</hi> But if the meaning be, That the <hi>whole form</hi> of a ſinners Juſtification properly taken, and as we find it ſpoken of in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, be <hi>not</hi> compriz'd in the Forgiveneſs of ſin, 'twill appear to be a Miſtake. Thoſe that thus Object, tell us our Juſtification conſiſts of <hi>two diſtinct parts.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Remiſſion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64072:22"/>of ſin,</hi> Secondly, <hi>Adjudging to be Righteous:</hi> Each ſtanding upon a <hi>distinct bottom,</hi> the firſt upon <hi>Chriſts paſſive obedience,</hi> and the other upon his <hi>Active</hi> (though in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we read not one Syllable of any ſuch thing.) Theſe two I have proved before are in the Scripture-method <hi>conjoyned:</hi> Whoever is by God, upon the belief of the Goſpel, for the ſake of Chriſt, <hi>judicially pardoned,</hi> is <hi>thereby Justified</hi> and accounted as <hi>Righteous,</hi> and the ſatisfaction of Chriſt is reckoned and imputed by God to all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, in thoſe <hi>effects,</hi> and for thoſe <hi>ends</hi> and <hi>purpoſes;</hi> nor can it be rationally ſuppoſed to be <hi>otherwiſe</hi> imputed: For <hi>no other</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Righteouſneſs performed, or Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made on my <hi>behalf,</hi> can come to be any <hi>other way</hi> juſtly accounted <hi>mine,</hi> then in the <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>advantages</hi> of it. It can never be a Juſt Judgment to adjudge <hi>me</hi> to have Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally performed <hi>my ſelf,</hi> what was actually done by <hi>another,</hi> though it was done on <hi>my behalf,</hi> and be reckoned to <hi>my account.</hi> There is no other poſſible way by which any man can come to be accounted Righteous in Judgment, but either by a righteouſneſs <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in our ſelves,</hi> (which does conſtitute us <hi>innocent,</hi>) or by the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi> made ours in a way of <hi>perſonal impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> (which muſt make us alſo to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64072:22"/>as <hi>innocents,</hi> and not as <hi>offenders.</hi>) The firſt is affirmed by the <hi>Papists,</hi> and the later by many Learned <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> The Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of both which opinions, I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after endeavour in this Diſcourſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fully return Anſwer to this and all other Objections of this nature.</p>
            <p>That Text <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 25. is much preſſed and inſiſted on; But upon great Miſtake, as will eaſily be made to appear. The words are, <hi>Who was delivered for our offences, and was raiſed again for our Justification.</hi> Which words are not to be taken as if there were <hi>two diſtinct ends</hi> in Chriſts <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> the one to obtain <hi>pardon of ſin,</hi> and the other to <hi>juſtifie,</hi> (And ſo to <hi>divide</hi> between them two, whereas in truth the Apoſtle makes them <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> thing) But the natural meaning and intendment of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in that text is this, That, <hi>All that Christ did, and ſuffered, was upon our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count:</hi> He was delivered to death upon the account of our ſins, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for our <hi>greateſt ſins</hi> and <hi>utmost Apostacy,</hi> (for that ſenſe is included in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and roſe again upon the <hi>ſame</hi> account, <hi>to justify us from the condemning power of them.</hi> By <hi>being delivered for our offences, and riſing again for our Justification,</hi> the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the <hi>ſame thing,</hi> which is, to <hi>justifie</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64072:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ſave</hi> us from <hi>our ſins:</hi> And the latter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is <hi>exegetical</hi> of the former. 'Tis to inſtruct us that Chriſts <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> that he tranſacted, had <hi>one</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, and was <hi>all</hi> in order to <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> end. For in ſome Texts we are ſaid to be <hi>justified by his Death,</hi> and <hi>by his Blood;</hi> ſo that he <hi>Dyed</hi> for our juſtification, as well as <hi>roſe again</hi> for it. The Scripture no where affords us the leaſt warrant to aſſign <hi>one</hi> diſtinct <hi>end</hi> to Chriſts <hi>death,</hi> and <hi>another</hi> to his <hi>reſurrection.</hi> Nay, the Apoſtle himſelf upon another occaſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. poſitively <hi>conjoyns</hi> them as <hi>inſeparable</hi> in their <hi>ends; For this end</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Chriſt both dyed and roſe again.</hi> Whatever Chriſt <hi>dyed</hi> for, he <hi>roſe again</hi> for. His Riſing again did not induce any farther, or other <hi>ends,</hi> then were his <hi>Death,</hi> but only <hi>compleat</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> the whole Deſign and Intendment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For although Chriſt dyed for our ſins, yet if he had not Riſen again, we could not have reap't the Fruit and Effect of his <hi>Death.</hi> His <hi>own</hi> Juſtification, as <hi>Mediator,</hi> and ſo <hi>ours,</hi> depending upon his Reſurrection as the ſupream and Glorious Effect of his <hi>Deity,</hi> and that <hi>whereby he was declared to be the Son of God mightily from heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64072:23"/>
            <p>Secondly, 'Tis <hi>Objected, That Remiſſion of ſin doth only take away the</hi> guilt, <hi>or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to</hi> puniſhment, <hi>but doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the</hi> Sin it ſelf; <hi>and therefore Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation cannot conſiſt in</hi> it. <hi>Although par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin do make as if ſin had never been in reſpect of the</hi> guilt <hi>of it, yet not in reſpect of the</hi> denomination <hi>of the</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. <hi>Although</hi> David <hi>was</hi> pardoned, <hi>yet his pardon did not make him a</hi> Juſt man <hi>in thoſe acts of his Murder and Adultery: He was truely a Murderer and an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer notwithſtanding. Juſtification doth not denominate a man to be</hi> Juſt, <hi>and a</hi> righteouſneſs <hi>is requiſite unto it. A man is not</hi> Juſtified, <hi>and therefore</hi> Juſt; <hi>but muſt be</hi> Juſt, <hi>and therefore</hi> Juſtified, <hi>in the order of</hi> Juſtification.</p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer in theſe three things. Firſt, by Gods forgiving of ſin in a Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial way, as much is done to obliterate and extinguiſh it in its proper denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as is <hi>poſſible;</hi> and nothing but Gods forgiveneſs could have done <hi>ſo much.</hi> For he forgiveth as the <hi>Supream Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>all:</hi> And his forgiveneſs is not only the effect of his <hi>mercy,</hi> but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64072:24"/>of all his infinite <hi>Attributes.</hi> He is pleaſed with a redundancy of Grace to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs himſelf in Scripture to us about this matter, that <hi>we might have a ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation therein.</hi> As firſt, <hi>That he will turn his face from our ſins, Pſal.</hi> 51. Secondly, <hi>That he will remember them no more,</hi> Iſa. 42. Thirdly, <hi>That he will not impute them,</hi> Pſal. 32. Fourthly, <hi>That he will caſt them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the depths of the ſea,</hi> Mica. 7. And fifthly, <hi>that he will caſt them behind his back,</hi> Iſa. 38. Now I ſay, Where God hath ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given ſin, all the <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>conſequences</hi> of it as ſuch an Action are utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; and ſo <hi>it ſelf ceaſeth</hi> after a ſort <hi>to be.</hi> And he that hath committed Acts of ſin, when he is Legally pardoned, is no more a <hi>Sinner,</hi> nor ought he in Juſtice ſo to be accounted: For, 'twas the <hi>judgment</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> by which he is <hi>Acquitted,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>de him ſo to be. 'Tis true, thoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acts do not naturally <hi>ceaſe to be,</hi> but all that was <hi>in</hi> thoſe Acts obnoxious to the Law, from whence their ſinfulneſs aroſe, upon Judicial pardon, <hi>legally ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be;</hi> and that is ſufficient in this caſe: For we are not, in the diſcourſe of this point, making inquiries into a <hi>natural,</hi> or <hi>metaphyſical</hi> exiſtence of things, but only into a <hi>judicial</hi> and <hi>legal.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64072:24"/>
            <p>Secondly, Let it be thus farther conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that nothing can more extinguiſh the denomination of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſinner,</hi> then Legal and Judicial <hi>pardon.</hi> As, take it in the preſent inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> in thoſe ſinful Acts of his: The Acts,
'tis true, were the <hi>ſame,</hi> naturally conſidered, <hi>after</hi> his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that they were <hi>before:</hi> but <hi>legally</hi> and <hi>forenſically</hi> conſidered, they were <hi>not:</hi> And how is it poſſible to be otherwiſe, but that the very <hi>acts</hi> muſt be ſtill <hi>naturally</hi> the <hi>ſame?</hi> For ſuppoſe the righteouſneſs of Chriſt to be <hi>perſonally imputed</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> (as thoſe that thus Object would have it to be,) to denominate him a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon, and ſo render him a fit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for Juſtification; ſuch Imputation will not make the Actions of his own ſin to be naturally otherwiſe then indeed they are, nor the Obliquity of them more ceaſe to be then it does by Forgiveneſs. There being no other poſſible way to bring an <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender</hi> in the judgment of the Law into a <hi>righteous</hi> eſtate and condition, but by <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial pardon.</hi> And if after ſuch pardon, what is here objected be true, that the denomination of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſinner</hi> as ſuch, notwithſtanding <hi>remain;</hi> it will unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably follow, by the ſtrict Doctrine or <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64072:25"/>imputation,</hi> that a man may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the proper denomination of a <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man</hi> and a <hi>ſinner</hi> at one and the ſame time, (which implyes a loud Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:) For a man may be accounted <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> in reſpect of Chriſts righteouſneſs, <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally</hi> made his <hi>own</hi> by <hi>imputation,</hi> and yet he may be juſtly denominated a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> however: For although his ſins be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and ceaſe to be, in reſpect of the <hi>guilt</hi> of them, yet not in reſpect of the <hi>deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the ſubject,</hi> as 'tis here Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. Whoever that was once an <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> comes to be juſtly accounted <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> muſt firſt be fully <hi>cleared</hi> from the <hi>denomination</hi> of an <hi>offender,</hi> for thoſe two are viſibly inconſiſtent in one ſubject. And nothing elſe can more Effect that, then <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, To the latter part of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, [That <hi>Justification doth denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a man to be juſt, and a righteouſneſs is requiſite to it: A man is not juſtified, and therefore juſt; but juſt, and therefore juſtified, in the order of Juſtification.</hi>] I Anſwer, The firſt thing affirmed herein; <hi>That Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication doth denominate a man to be juſt, and a righteouſneſs is requiſite to it,</hi> is thus true: That Juſtification neceſſarily <hi>ſuppoſeth</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64072:25"/>a man to be <hi>juſt,</hi> and it includeth the notion of his being ſo one of theſe two wayes, either <hi>inherently,</hi> or <hi>legally</hi> and <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially;</hi> the one relates to an <hi>innocent</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Juſtification, the other to an <hi>offenders:</hi> And when juſtified, they are <hi>both alike juſt</hi> in <hi>Law-ſenſe,</hi> though <hi>differently</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the <hi>manner</hi> of their Juſtification, and in their <hi>antecedent condition</hi> to it. He that is not juſtified upon <hi>inherent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> but is an <hi>offender,</hi> he can only ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at the ſtate of a juſt man by <hi>Legal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitment in judgment,</hi> and by having a <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> in <hi>law</hi> paſs <hi>for him:</hi> For whatever <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> he makes, (though it be true, that there is virtually contained a <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> in <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi>) yet being actually an <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender</hi> in the judgment of the Law, till the Plea of his ſatisfaction be <hi>accepted,</hi> and he thereupon <hi>judicially acquitted,</hi> he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be accounted of as <hi>righteous,</hi> and ſo can never be righteous <hi>previouſly</hi> to his <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> To ſpeak of a <hi>previous righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> properly ſo called, requiſite to an offenders Juſtification, ſuch as will juſtifie and defend him in Judgment, has no tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſenſe in it: For it ſuppoſeth a man to come under the notion of an <hi>offender,</hi> and a <hi>righteous</hi> perſon at the ſame time. This
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64072:26"/>only is true in that caſe, that a ſufficient <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> muſt be pleaded for the pardon and Juſtification of an <hi>offender</hi> before a <hi>righteous Tribunal:</hi> And that alone can be plenary ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and cannot be any thing elſe. And that, upon <hi>acceptance,</hi> muſt needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Pardon.</hi> And the natural End both of <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> and <hi>pardon,</hi> is to <hi>re-inſtate</hi> an <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender</hi> into a <hi>righteous condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing affirmed, <hi>That a man is not juſtified, and therefore juſt; but juſt, and therefore juſtified,</hi> is a great Miſtake: For it relates Juſtification ſolely and ſingly to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents,</hi> and renders the Juſtification of <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders</hi> (about which the Scripture is only converſant) utterly <hi>impracticable</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</hi> Perſons <hi>inherently righteous</hi> are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied becauſe <hi>found ſo,</hi> and their Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is but <hi>affirmative</hi> and <hi>declarative</hi> of ſuch inherent righteouſneſs; But <hi>offenders</hi> are brought into the ſtate of Juſt men upon <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal pardon</hi> and <hi>diſcharge:</hi> Nor can any Satisfaction in its nature operate farther.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, 'Tis <hi>Objected, That God requires a</hi> poſitive righteouſneſs <hi>of us, conformable unto his</hi> Law <hi>in the perfect obligation of it: And therefore it follows, that</hi> meer remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin, <hi>under what diſtinction ſoever,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64072:26"/>cannot be our</hi> righteouſneſs. <hi>Remiſſion of ſin frees from</hi> puniſhment, <hi>but 'tis</hi> perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience <hi>that entitles us to</hi> eternal happineſs.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, <hi>Legal ſinleſs-righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> which the Law requires, God accepts <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> 'Tis <hi>Goſpel-righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> we are now to enquire after. If God had not accepted <hi>Chriſt</hi> in our ſtead, and his <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to anſwer for all our <hi>oblige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to the <hi>law,</hi> as a Law of <hi>works,</hi> and <hi>ſuper-induced</hi> a <hi>better covenant</hi> thereupon; this Argument had been good: But ſeeing he has, 'tis of no force at all. The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. that <hi>Chriſt is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth.</hi> To underſtand which expreſſion of the Apoſtle aright, we muſt conſider, <hi>Finem alicujus rei</hi> (as the School-men ſpeak) <hi>dici dupliciter, in quem tendit res vel naturaliter, vel ex ordinatione Agentis.</hi> The End to which the Law naturally tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was ſuch a particular <hi>perſonal ſinleſs-righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> in <hi>each</hi> man as he might <hi>juſtifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> upon, and claim the <hi>reward promiſed</hi> as a <hi>debt due.</hi> This end the <hi>Jews</hi> purſued and ſought after, and the Apoſtle rejects, as appears in the <hi>3d ver.</hi> But the end to which the Law tended <hi>by the ordination of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64072:27"/>God,</hi> was <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſs</hi> to make <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> for our <hi>diſobedience,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to introduce another <hi>method</hi> of <hi>Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> in a way of <hi>ſaith</hi> and <hi>believing,</hi> that we might no longer be under a Law of <hi>works,</hi> but under a Law of <hi>grace.</hi> The Law could not attain its <hi>natural end,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>mans impotency;</hi> and ſo
'twas <hi>a ſchoolmaſter to bring us to Chriſt.</hi> Nor did it <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> for the Law required an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinning righteouſneſs</hi> from <hi>every particular perſon,</hi> and not from Chriſt to ſatisfie for <hi>all others:</hi> That depends purely upon <hi>Gods ordination.</hi> To all <hi>unbelievers</hi> the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill in <hi>force</hi> as it was firſt given, and the <hi>wrath of God abides upon them thereby:</hi> but to thoſe that <hi>believe,</hi> and ſo are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kingdom of the Mediator, the Law is <hi>not in force,</hi> as a Law of <hi>works,</hi> but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>establiſhed by Him as part of the New Law,</hi> and upon the ſame <hi>gracious terms</hi> that all other <hi>goſpel-precepts</hi> are: For the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>we are not under the Law, but under grace;</hi> and yet tells us alſo, <hi>the law is eſtabliſhed by the Goſpel.</hi> All that diſcuſs this point, ought ſtill to conſider, that our Juſtification is not <hi>Legal</hi> but <hi>Evangelical:</hi> For we are juſtified with reſpect to the Law that is intereſted in <hi>Chriſts ſatisfaction,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64072:27"/>upon performance of the <hi>Goſpel-Condition,</hi> and not otherwiſe. 'Tis not by the Law of <hi>Works,</hi> any way conſidered, that we are Actually and Perſonally juſtified. The Apoſtle ſo concludes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.38. <hi>A man is justified without the deeds of the law:</hi> But 'tis by the <hi>law of faith.</hi> Whatever the Law of <hi>works</hi> requires, God has accepted of <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> for our <hi>non-performance</hi> of it, in our <hi>Surety</hi> and <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> and has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered him to offer ſalvation upon the terms of a <hi>better covenant.</hi> And the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God</hi> (the Apoſtle tells us) is <hi>now manifeſted without the law.</hi> Our Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is now upon the terms of a <hi>new recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring law of grace:</hi> And 'tis the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>that</hi> we are now only obliged to perform. When we are impleaded at the <hi>Bar</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> we <hi>plead ſatisfaction in Chriſt</hi> for our Non-performance; when we are impleaded at the Bar of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and put to prove our <hi>perſonal intereſt</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety</hi> in that ſatisfaction, then we are obliged to manifeſt our <hi>performance</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel-condition,</hi> and evidence the <hi>truth</hi> of our <hi>faith,</hi> by which we are intituled to it: Our Plea muſt then lye <hi>there.</hi> So that with reference to the Law we are Juſtified, that is, Judicially pardoned and acquitted in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64072:28"/>judgment, upon <hi>ſatisfaction made;</hi> with reference to the Goſpel, upon <hi>performance</hi> of the <hi>condition.</hi> And <hi>faith</hi> looks <hi>both wayes,</hi> reſpects both the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> and comprizeth all that is requiſite to our Juſtification, with reference to <hi>both.</hi> All the Charge of the Law it Anſwers, <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Objecti,</hi> in reſpect of its <hi>Object,</hi> which is <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And all that is required by the Goſpel, <hi>ratione ſui,</hi> as being <hi>it ſelf</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the Condition annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. To ſuppoſe that every Juſtified perſon, as neceſſarily requiſite to his Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, muſt be <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>perſonally</hi> poſſeſſed of all that <hi>unſinning obedience,</hi> the ſtrict rules of the Law required, is a great <hi>miſtake;</hi> for none was ever ſo but <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> who became a Publick Satisfaction and Ranſome for the <hi>whole.</hi> Should any man now be Juſtified under the law of faith, upon a <hi>ſtrict performance</hi> of the law of <hi>works,</hi> any way conſidered, the Law would not then be <hi>relaxed,</hi> but ſtill <hi>ſtrictly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Now the truth is, the Law is neither <hi>executed</hi> nor <hi>abrogated,</hi> but <hi>relaxed</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced with. Executed</hi> it is not, for who then could be ſaved? And the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>There is no</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64072:28"/>
               <hi>abrogated it is not:</hi> For 'tis in <hi>full force</hi> (a dreadful conſideration to the wicked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing part of the world!) with all its <hi>rigour</hi> againſt all thoſe that do not believe and obey the Goſpel; and under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel it ſelf, though we are freed from the <hi>curſe</hi> of the Law, yet we are ſtill under the <hi>government</hi> of the Law in the ſenſe before mentioned: The <hi>condemning</hi> power is only taken off, the <hi>commanding</hi> power is ſtill continued: And, as ſome ſay, (though I think ſuch ought well to conſider what the Apoſtle ſayes, 1 <hi>Cor. ch.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 22.) not <hi>all</hi> the <hi>condemning</hi> power neither in matters <hi>temporal,</hi> for the beſt men are ſtill ſubjected to <hi>death natural</hi> and many <hi>ſorrows.</hi> And beſides, either a man muſt be poſſeſſed of ſuch Legal Righteouſneſs <hi>inherently,</hi> or <hi>imputatively;</hi> Inherently he cannot, for the Scripture tells us, that <hi>by the works of the Law no man living can be juſtified:</hi> Nor can he be by way of <hi>imputation perſonally</hi> poſſeſſed of it: For <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> did not, nor <hi>could not,</hi> in <hi>perſon,</hi> perform <hi>all thoſe individual acts</hi> the Law requires from <hi>every perſon</hi> that is Juſtified by it: For, when Chriſt is ſaid <hi>to fulfill all righteouſneſs,</hi> 'tis meant all made neceſſary by the <hi>law of his Mediatorſhip</hi> for himſelf to perform, and not what <hi>every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64072:29"/>man</hi> was bound to perform. And therefore no <hi>ſuch imputation</hi> can ever be ſuppoſed, unleſs we will ſuppoſe God to account <hi>me,</hi> to have done that <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt never did himſelf,</hi> and in the Nature of the thing
'twas <hi>impoſſible</hi> he <hi>ſhould</hi> do: Or elſe to account <hi>me</hi> to have done in <hi>mine own perſon, all</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did in <hi>his perſon,</hi> and ſo to be <hi>righteous</hi> in the very <hi>ſame ſpotleſs way,</hi> and to the <hi>ſame tranſcendent degree</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was. The only difference between thoſe that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the form of Juſtification to conſiſt in the <hi>pardon of ſin,</hi> and thoſe that ſay 'tis requiſite beſides forgiveneſs of ſin, farther to take in the <hi>righteouſneſs of Chriſt by imputation,</hi> and that we ſhould be pronounced righteous in judgment <hi>therein,</hi> is this, Whether Chriſts righteouſneſs ſhall be reckoned and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us in a way of <hi>Satisfaction made for our ſins and diſobedience,</hi> upon a ſincere <hi>belief of the Goſpel,</hi> and we reckoned <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> upon <hi>that account,</hi> or whether it ſhall be ſo imputed, as to be <hi>perſonally</hi> reckoned <hi>our own,</hi> and to be adjudged righteous by God, not <hi>for,</hi> but in that very righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: In both caſes, our <hi>Justification</hi> is bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom'd upon <hi>Chriſts alone righteouſneſs,</hi> and the <hi>imputation</hi> of it to <hi>us.</hi> If the firſt be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64072:29"/>true, then 'tis undenyable (contrary to what is objected) that our <hi>Juſtification</hi> is our <hi>pardon;</hi> and our <hi>pardon</hi> upon <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made</hi> and <hi>accepted,</hi> and the condition performed, is that upon which we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted <hi>perſonally righteous:</hi> For <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> made for an <hi>offender</hi> naturally and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily operates <hi>that way,</hi> and cannot operate any <hi>other</hi> in <hi>judgment:</hi> the vertue of it muſt needs be iſſued in <hi>pardon.</hi> Now that the firſt is much <hi>likelier</hi> to be true, and has much more of <hi>rational probability</hi> in it, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Scripture-teſtimony, where we are ſaid to be <hi>Ranſom'd, Redeem'd, Purchaſed, Bought with a price,</hi> which all relate to <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi>) then the Later, does from hence appear; by that we are Juſtified as <hi>Sinners,</hi> upon <hi>compenſation</hi> made for our <hi>ſins,</hi> and are brought into a Righteous ſtate by the <hi>pardon</hi> of them, which is plainly the truth of our caſe, and a thing eaſie to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. By the <hi>other,</hi> we are made to be juſtified as <hi>Innocents,</hi> which is not the truth of our caſe, unleſs we will ſuppoſe God to account us to have done <hi>all</hi> that <hi>Chriſt did,</hi> that is, to have performed all righteouſneſs without ſin, which in <hi>fact</hi> was not ſo.</p>
            <p>This Objection therefore is wholly grounded upon a Miſtake. We obtain not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64072:30"/>Heaven as <hi>the reward of the Law,</hi> but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>promiſes of the Goſpel.</hi> Our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern is not upon what Terms the <hi>Law</hi> does juſtifie, but how the <hi>Goſpel</hi> does juſtifie: Our own <hi>ſins</hi> have rendred impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable the <hi>juſtifying</hi> power of the Law, and <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> has <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeded</hi> the <hi>condemning</hi> power of. it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <head>SECT. III</head>
            <p>I Come, in the ſecond place, to conſider, <hi>What is the material procuring Cauſe of Juſtification before God?</hi> And the Anſwer to it in general, is this, 'tis a <hi>Satisfaction made, ſuitable to his Juſtice, for the breach of his Law.</hi> And this ſatisfaction conſiſts in <hi>the whole Active and Paſſive obedience of our Saviour,</hi> intirely taken together, and the infinite <hi>merit</hi> thereof, with which God declares himſelf ſo abundantly <hi>ſatisfied</hi> and <hi>well pleaſed,</hi> that he <hi>Relaxeth</hi> the Law of Works thereupon, <hi>diſpenſeth</hi> with the <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour</hi> of it, and <hi>ſuperinduceth another Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> upon the terms of which we are <hi>juſtified</hi> and <hi>ſaved.</hi> God does not, upon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64072:30"/>ſatisfaction made for the breach of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works, thereupon immediately pardon and ſave us <hi>by that:</hi> But he relieves and releaſeth us from the obligation we lay under to it, and proclaims a <hi>new Law,</hi> and enters into <hi>another Covenant;</hi> And 'tis upon the <hi>terms</hi> of <hi>that</hi> we are actually par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and juſtified. The Righteouſneſs and Satisfaction of <hi>Chriſt</hi> fully anſwers for us, in reſpect of the <hi>Law:</hi> We ſtand no more obliged to it, a 'tis a <hi>Law of Works;</hi> and 'tis the procuring Cauſe and formal Reaſon of the <hi>new Law</hi> of the <hi>ſaving Covenant,</hi> upon the terms of which, we are pardoned and juſtified, and which is in its nature but a <hi>method</hi> of <hi>forgiveneſs,</hi> and that place the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt bears in point of Juſtification: So that the whole is <hi>Origina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> in our <hi>Redeemers Satisfaction,</hi> and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed thereby; the ineſtimable value and merit whereof, reſults from theſe four things, the <hi>dignity</hi> of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> the <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>ſpontaniety</hi> of his undertaking, the <hi>undertaking</hi> it ſelf, and the <hi>ordination</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the caſe; had there not been a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of all <hi>theſe,</hi> the ſatisfaction had been defective and ineffectual, the Goſpel had never been publiſhed, Death and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation had ſtill reigned, and the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64072:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>Law had continued ſtill in its full force and vertue.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What a ſtupendious <hi>dignity</hi> was there in Chriſts <hi>Perſon, in whom the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelt bodily?</hi> 'Tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we ſhould be redeem'd by his blood, when it was <hi>the blood of God,</hi> and that <hi>the righteouſneſs of this one ſhould redound to All, for the Juſtification of life,</hi> as 'tis expreſſed <hi>Rom.</hi> 5 18. when <hi>in him dwelt all fulneſs.</hi> The Actions and Sufferings of ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt needs be of unſpeakable value, becauſe of his own tranſcendent Eminency above all creatures, yea even <hi>Angels,</hi> for <hi>he is Gods Fellow,</hi> and was in the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Whatever was done and ſuffered by a perſon ſo qualified, in whom concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred all the perfection both of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Divine nature, muſt needs be of <hi>infinite value,</hi> and of <hi>deſert</hi> and <hi>merit</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all bounds of imagination: 'Tis no wonder we ſhould be <hi>bought</hi> with ſuch a <hi>price:</hi> and yet nothing <hi>leſs</hi> then this can we ſuppoſe (without impeaching the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, who ſaw to bring it about this way) could have anſwer'd for mans diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, have ſtopt the current of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice, and made a ſatisfaction for that Eternity of puniſhment that became due to us.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:64072:31"/>
            <p>Secondly, How free and <hi>voluntary,</hi> what a meer act of <hi>Choice</hi> was Chriſts ſufeeption of his Mediatory work! How far was he exalted beyond the reach of all obligation, or poſſibility of any Addition! No Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could oblige him that was God, nor could the Divine nature lay a Conſtraint upon it ſelf; 'tis an eſſential property of the Godhead to act <hi>freely.</hi> 'Tis true, when he was man he was <hi>obliged</hi> as a <hi>man;</hi> but he was under no engagement to <hi>become man.</hi> A Servants work and a Creatures homage was due from him indeed, when a <hi>Creature</hi> and a <hi>Servant;</hi> but 'twas his own free <hi>choice</hi> that brought him into the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>either.</hi> Nothing but the workings of his own infinite bowells of Compaſſion over the fallen poſterity of Apoſtate <hi>Adam,</hi> could bring him to Tabernaclo in fleſh, and take up his abode with the children of Men. In a word, he <hi>freely</hi> and out of <hi>choice</hi> became man, and lived a life Natural: And as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>reſign'd</hi> up his life unto death, and became a <hi>free-will-offering</hi> to God: So himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>I lay down my life, no man taketh it from me.</hi> And <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.25. he tells us, <hi>He came to Give his life a ranſom for many.</hi> And had not this been ſo, God who is infinitely juſt, could not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64072:32"/>have <hi>puniſhed</hi> him in whom there was found <hi>no guilt:</hi> Nor had it been Equal with God to accept <hi>him</hi> on <hi>our behalf,</hi> unleſs he had <hi>freely</hi> eſpouſed <hi>our intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, How admirable is the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking</hi> of Chriſt <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> Firſt, to <hi>aſſume humane nature,</hi> from the very firſt moment of which aſſumption began the ſtate of his <hi>humiliation,</hi> and in that nature to yield a perfect obedience to all the Laws of God, to which mankind were obliged, and in the ſame to undergo the penalty due up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>breach,</hi> ſubmit himſelf to become a <hi>Curſe</hi> for us! What an <hi>amazing</hi> conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is it, that the <hi>Lord of all,</hi> ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>man,</hi> in <hi>the form of a ſervant,</hi> and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject himſelf to an obedience to all his own Laws, yea even of thoſe that were but the <hi>ſhadow</hi> (as were the Ceremonial) of which he, as man incarnate, was the ſubſtance: And that he that was without all ſin, ſhould ſubmit to thoſe Inſtitutions that were grounded upon the ſuppoſition of <hi>ſin,</hi> and whoſe End and Tendency had a direct re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to it; ſuch was <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.</hi> And yet ſo he was pleaſed to <hi>fulfill all righteouſneſs,</hi> to do all the Law required, and yet to ſuffer what it <hi>threatned.</hi> Now conſidering that he lay under no obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64072:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>with reſpect to himſelf for the doing of any of this, what a vaſt ſtock of <hi>Merit</hi> muſt needs be treaſur'd up for thoſe to whom He and the Father ſhall pleaſe to <hi>impute</hi> it! 'Tis this undertaking of Chriſt, that could alone <hi>face divine Juſtice,</hi> and at the dreadful Tribunal of the great and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Jehovah,</hi> be admitted as a ſufficient <hi>Plea</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for an <hi>open Rebellion</hi> from <hi>duſt</hi> and <hi>aſhes</hi> againſt Him. His obedience to the Law qualified with ſuch infinite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and repreſenting us in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, being both the <hi>Son of God</hi> and the <hi>Son of man, redintigrated</hi> the honour of the Law to as great a degree, as if it had never been broken: And his voluntary ſubjecting himſelf to the <hi>Curſe</hi> and <hi>penalty</hi> of it, made as great and honourable a <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to it, as if, being broken, the <hi>utmoſt penalty</hi> had been <hi>inſticted</hi> upon <hi>every particular Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, That which compleated, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and crowned this ſatisfaction, was <hi>Gods ordination:</hi> A <hi>Statute</hi> made in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> that ſo Chriſt being himſelf freely willing, ſhould do, and that ſhould be <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted</hi> in ſo doing, obtain his End, and <hi>ſee the travel of his ſoul, and be ſatisfied.</hi> In the 10th. of the <hi>Heb.</hi> we find this fully expreſſed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64072:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>by a Quotation out of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> where <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks in the perſon of <hi>Chriſt: Then ſaid I, lo I come, in the volume of the book it is written of me to do they will O God.</hi> And in the 10th. <hi>ver.</hi> the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>By that Will we are ſanctified, by the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up of the body of Chriſt.</hi> In the 3d. of St. <hi>Mat.</hi> upon Chriſts being baptized, a voice came from Heaven and declared, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:</hi> Not only with his <hi>Perſon,</hi> but his <hi>Office,</hi> with his <hi>mediatory</hi> work and imployment, as being of <hi>mine own ordination</hi> and <hi>appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Upon Chriſts voluntary underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to aſſume our nature, and in that nature to repreſent <hi>us,</hi> and to ſubject him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a Law of Mediatorſhip, ſuch a Law, as the performance whereof, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a compleate ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice, God was pleaſed to <hi>ordain</hi> it ſo to be, and that all that he Did and Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in that Nature, ſhould be <hi>accepted</hi> on our behalf and reckoned and accounted to our advantage, and that Mankind ſhould obtain ſalvation thereby. This Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God was the <hi>Broad Seal of Heaven</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed to all Chriſt did. This <hi>ratified</hi> on <hi>high,</hi> was done here <hi>below,</hi> and made all the tranſaction of Chriſt on <hi>Earth</hi> to paſs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64072:33"/>currant in <hi>Heaven:</hi> Had not this been <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident, nothing</hi> could have prevailed: Had not God <hi>determin'd above,</hi> that what Chriſt did and ſuffer'd on <hi>earth,</hi> ſhould be that ſatisfaction to his Juſtice for the ſins of the world, in which he would acquieſee and be well pleaſed, and upon which he would ordain the Bleſſing, even Life for evermore, No pardon had been proclaimed, we had been yet in our ſins, and the ſtate of all mankind had been no better then that of the fallen Angels, and final Impenitents, even <hi>a fearful looking for of Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two great Miſtakes have ariſen in the minds of many, and of many Worthy and Good men, about this matter, the rectifying of which is of great and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry importance. Firſt, Some have ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that</hi> The whole of Chriſts ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for our ſins conſiſts in his Paſſive obedience: And that his Active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is imputed to us, to conſtitute us Perſonally righteous in God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count —. <hi>And ſo Disjoyn the Active and Paſſive righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and apply them to Diſtinct ends and purpoſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:64072:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This will appear in it ſelf no way Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and without the leaſt warrant from Scripture. Firſt, Each of theſe have their proper Intereſt in, and do reſpectively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the repairing the honour of Gods injured and violated Law, and do joyntly compleat Chriſts ſatisfaction. The honour of the Law is in a twofold reſpect to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; in the <hi>preceptive</hi> part, and in the <hi>threatning</hi> part. To what a degree is the Law honoured in the firſt reſpect, by the <hi>perfect obedience</hi> of <hi>God-man!</hi> How is the <hi>Juſtice, Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed and ſolemnized thereby, when <hi>he</hi> diſdained not to become <hi>obedient to it!</hi> And to no leſs a degree is it honoured in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect; for by his dying and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, 'tis eminently declared what <hi>ſin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved!</hi> And the Juſtice of the Law is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evidenced in its <hi>threatning</hi> and <hi>penalty:</hi> So that theſe two are by no means to be <hi>ſevered,</hi> for they contribute <hi>inſeparably</hi> by their Effects, to the great work of making <hi>one intire ſatisfaction</hi> for the ſins of the world, and procuring our Pardon. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, They are in their own nature <hi>conjoyn'd,</hi> and mutually participate of the qualities each of other: For Chriſts <hi>active</hi> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs was all <hi>paſſive:</hi> His coming from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64072:34"/>Heaven in the form of a Servant, and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience to the Law here upon Earth had all vaſt <hi>humiliation</hi> and <hi>ſuffering</hi> in it: And he himſelf was <hi>active</hi> alſo in all he <hi>ſuffered,</hi> to the higheſt degree, for 'twas an act of his own free <hi>choice,</hi> without the leaſt <hi>conſtraint</hi> ſo to do. No man could have <hi>taken</hi> his life, had not himſelf made <hi>choice</hi> of death. Thirdly, To disjoyn theſe two, and aſcribe to them Diſtinct and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ends; to ſay, (that Chriſts <hi>paſſive</hi> obedience is imputed to us, to procure <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> of all <hi>ſin;</hi> and his <hi>active</hi> obedience is imputed to us, to conſtitute us <hi>righteous,</hi>) ſeems dangerous in its conſequence, and tends to make one of them appear altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>uſeleſs:</hi> For if all ſin, original and actual, of omiſſion and commiſſion were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered for and pardoned, what need we <hi>more?</hi> We muſt needs be brought into a <hi>righteous</hi> condition thereby: Becauſe the leaſt <hi>defect</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> is ſome <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>ſin;</hi> and where there is no degree of <hi>ſin,</hi> there muſt needs be <hi>perfect righteouſneſs.</hi> So if all the <hi>active righteouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt were <hi>perſonally</hi> by God in judgement <hi>rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned</hi> to be <hi>ours,</hi> we could not at the ſame time be accounted as <hi>ſinners,</hi> but in the utmoſt <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>innocents:</hi> And if
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64072:35"/>ſo, What need were there of Chriſts <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,</hi> or of any <hi>expiation</hi> for <hi>ſin?</hi> The Law did not require <hi>ſuffering</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> both, but obliged us either to obey, or elſe to undergo the penalty. How much better is the plain <hi>Scripture-account</hi> of this matter, where theſe <hi>two</hi> are by God, and Chriſt himſelf in their <hi>end</hi> every where <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd;</hi> By which we are told, that the <hi>whole</hi> of what Chriſt <hi>did,</hi> and <hi>ſuffered,</hi> in all its circumſtances unitedly conſidered, is as <hi>one intire price</hi> of ineſtimable value, by way of <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> and valuable <hi>conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> paved unto God, and by him ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, for the redemption and Salvation of all ſuch who ſubmit to the <hi>terms,</hi> and perform the <hi>condition</hi> of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſecond Miſtake about this matter, is this: Some have conceived, that both the Active and Paſſive righteouſneſs of Chriſt are ſo made ours by a</hi> perſonal imputation, <hi>that</hi> we our ſelves <hi>are accounted by God in judgment to have</hi> done, <hi>and</hi> ſuffered thoſe very things, <hi>that Chriſt himſelf in his own perſon, did, and ſuffered.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64072:35"/>
            <p>This conception is ſo Groſs, that it is not only to be reckoned amongſt ſuch things as <hi>are hard to be underſtood,</hi> but amongſt ſuch things as are <hi>impoſſible</hi> to be accounted for to any common underſtanding. The no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>imputation</hi> in general, is no way to be oppoſed (though we are no where told in Scripture, <hi>in terminis, that Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is imputed to us,</hi>) that is, 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for us to partake of the <hi>benefits</hi> and <hi>advantages</hi> of what was done by <hi>another,</hi> as done in our <hi>ſtead,</hi> and upon our <hi>account,</hi> without ſome ſort of <hi>imputation.</hi> God is pleaſed that the <hi>whole</hi> of what Chriſt did, and ſuffered, in the <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>advantages</hi> of it, ſhould accrue to <hi>us</hi> and <hi>our account,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he accepted <hi>him</hi> on <hi>our behalf,</hi> and in <hi>our ſtead,</hi> and that <hi>we</hi> ſhould reap all the <hi>fruit</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> of his <hi>Mediatorſhip.</hi> And in <hi>this ſenſe</hi> God is pleaſed to <hi>impute</hi> his whole Mediatory tranſaction unto <hi>us,</hi> but no <hi>otherwiſe.</hi> The whole of Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is imputed to us, as made <hi>For us,</hi> (and ſo he is <hi>the Lord our righteouſneſs</hi>) but not as made <hi>By us,</hi> but actually made by <hi>him.</hi> And what can be more deſired, then to reap all the <hi>benefits</hi> of Chriſts whole un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and upon the account of it, and its being accepted of God on our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64072:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be <hi>pardoned, juſtified, ſanctified</hi> and <hi>ſaved;</hi> and as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it, <hi>to have Chriſt made to us of God</hi> (that is, as the Fundamental <hi>cauſe, procurer,</hi> and <hi>ſpring</hi> of them, a common <hi>head</hi> from whence they are all derived to us as his <hi>body</hi>) <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, righteouſneſs, ſanctification and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Thoſe that will preſs the point far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and inſiſt upon <hi>perſonal</hi> imputation to every believer what Chriſt did, ought well to conſider theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If every believer be <hi>perſonally righteous</hi> before God in the very <hi>individual Acts of Chriſts righteouſneſs,</hi> one of theſe two things will thence enſue: Either that Chriſt in his own perſon did perform all the particular acts of righteouſneſs required, as due from <hi>each ſaved perſon;</hi> or elſe that every is ſaved perſons righteouſneſs before God, is <hi>identically</hi> and <hi>numerically</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> with Chriſts in his publick capacity, as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, and ſo every ſaved perſon is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally righteous, with a righteouſneſs that has a ſtock of <hi>merit</hi> in it, ſufficient to ſave the world) unleſs you will ſay Chriſt had <hi>ſome</hi> righteouſneſs that belong'd to him as <hi>Mediator,</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> that did <hi>not,</hi> which is abſurd to affirm; for 'tis plain, all he did, he did as Mediator, nor had he any
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64072:36"/>any concern in the world but as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and none of his <hi>actions</hi> can be ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from his <hi>Office,</hi> being all purſuant of <hi>it.</hi> (The firſt will be granted was not, nor had a poſſibility to be; and yet no man can be perſonally righteous with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Law, but by an exact per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of <hi>every tittle</hi> and <hi>iota</hi> the Law required from him. And the other has two very groſs abſurdities in it. Firſt, That we ſhould be accounted to have done that which was done long before we were in a capacity to do <hi>any thing:</hi> And ſecondly, That we ſhould be reckoned perſonally righteous with the righteouſneſs of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> When firſt, There is not a poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that Man, or Angel could perform any one Action, with the Circumſtances, or in the Manner as he did. Secondly, Much of what he did, was in its nature <hi>unlawfull</hi> for any <hi>elſe</hi> to undertake. And thirdly, The Whole of what he did was peculiarly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated and appurtenant to his <hi>Office,</hi> as he was <hi>Mediator,</hi> and cannot be ſuited to any other perſon, nor is any part of it <hi>transferrable,</hi> or <hi>imputable</hi> to any <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> otherwiſe then in its <hi>operations</hi> and <hi>effects:</hi> For he neither did nor ſuffered the very <hi>idem</hi> that we are obliged to; for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64072:37"/>then he muſt have particularly done <hi>all</hi> the Law required from us, and have ſuffered to <hi>eternity.</hi> But he mad <hi>ſuch</hi> a ſatisfaction to God for our Non-performance, and on our behalf, as became him as <hi>Mediator,</hi> and ſuch as that God is pleaſed thereupon to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> the <hi>ſtrict</hi> and <hi>rigorous execution</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and to bring us under a <hi>better Covenant.</hi> Our caſe is not ſtrictly that of a <hi>Debtor,</hi> but of <hi>Rebellious Subjects,</hi> nor ſtand we in our ſins related to God as a <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor,</hi> but as a <hi>Supream Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Judge:</hi> Nor did Chriſt ſuſtain properly the place of a <hi>Surety</hi> to pay individually and identically our <hi>Debt,</hi> but of a <hi>Mediator</hi> tomake <hi>repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to divine Juſtice by <hi>another</hi> way, then putting the Law in <hi>execution</hi> againſt <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If every juſtified perſon be juſtified in judgment by the very <hi>acts</hi> of Chriſts perſonal righteouſneſs, accounted to him as his <hi>own,</hi> it will then follow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond any good anſwer, that every man is juſtified <hi>by the works of the Law:</hi> For Chriſts perſonal righteouſneſs, with reſpect to which he was juſtified as Mediator, and approved of God to become a ſufficient Saviour, was a <hi>Legal righteouſneſs</hi> and not an <hi>Evangelical.</hi> This if ſincere, though imperfect, will be accepted from us for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64072:37"/>Chriſts ſake, but would not ſo have been accepted from Chriſt for our Juſtification, nor can it be well affirmed that Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and obey'd his own Goſpel. That lyes on <hi>our part</hi> to perform. Now that we ſhould be juſtified by the <hi>works of the law,</hi> is confuted by many Texts: <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>Therefore we conclude, that a man is juſtified by faith without the deeds of the law.</hi> And <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>But that no nun is juſtified by the Law in the ſight of God, is evident, for the juſt ſhall live by Faith;</hi> and ſo in many other Texts: And the whole ſcope of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his diſcourſes of Juſtification, is to eſtabliſh this point, <hi>That no man is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by an unſinning obedience perform'd to the Law,</hi> and ſo Not by <hi>works,</hi> but by <hi>believing,</hi> and in the way of <hi>Goſpel-faith,</hi> which God is pleaſed out of Grace to accept and account for <hi>righteouſneſs.</hi> Nor will it be to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſay [it is one thing to be juſtified by our own obedience to the Law, and another thing to be juſtified by <hi>Chriſts obedience imputed.</hi>] For, if his obedience be <hi>ſo</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, as that we are accounted by God in judgment <hi>perſonally</hi> to have <hi>done</hi> what <hi>Chriſt did,</hi> it is all one as to this matter, and we are as much juſtified by the Law, and do as much live in the works thereof,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64072:38"/>as if we had in our own proper perſons per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed an unſinning obedience to it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if the rigid notion of <hi>imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſhould be admitted as true; then every particular perſon that is ſaved, did <hi>merit his own ſalvation.</hi> For, if the very Acts of Chriſt be reckoned as ours, and ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as if done by us, the <hi>effects</hi> muſt needs be imputed ſo too. If I am reckoned by God in my own perſon to have performed that righteouſneſs that does merit my Juſtification, I muſt of neceſſity be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to have <hi>merited</hi> my Juſtification. And beſides all this, many the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and unſound principles of <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianiſm</hi> have their riſe from this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; I chuſe to expreſs it in the words of Reverend Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> in his <hi>Diſcourſe of Juſtification. I inferr</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that they are dangerouſly miſtaken, who think that a believer is righteous in the ſight of God, with the ſelf-ſame Active and Paſſive righteouſneſs wherewith Chriſt was righteous; m though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſuffered in Chriſt, and obeyed in Chriſt, and were as righteous in Gods eſteem as Chriſt himſelf, having his perſonal righteouſneſs made perſonally theirs by imputation. This is their fundamental miſtake, and from hence</hi> (tanquam ex equo Trojano) <hi>iſſues out a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64072:38"/>throng of ſuch falſe and corrupt Deductions as theſe as, That God ſees no ſin in his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: That a believer need not pray for the Pardon of fin, but only for the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of it: That God loved</hi> Noah <hi>when Drunk, and</hi> David <hi>when acting Murder and Adultery.</hi> — And many more ſuch conſequences that worthy perſon men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe paſſages of Scripture that ſeem moſt to countenance this opinion, and are chiefly inſiſted on for the proof of it, are theſe three.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.25. He hath made him to be ſin for us, that knew no ſin, that we might be made the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God in him. <hi>From whence it is thus urged.</hi> How did Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſin for us? Not by inherency, but by imputation: So do we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Righteouſneſs of God in him.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, I ſay, <hi>Chriſt became</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for us,</hi> that is, <hi>a ſacrifice for ſin:</hi> For ſo it ſignifies, as well as barely <hi>Sin;</hi> as alſo the Latin <hi>piaculum</hi> which is often taken for a <hi>ſacrifice of expiation,</hi> as well as <hi>Sin:</hi> And in the <hi>Septuagint</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is frequently
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64072:39"/>uſed to ſignifie a <hi>ſacrifice for ſin:</hi> And this is an expreſſion relating to the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> And the proper rendering of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a <hi>ſin offering.</hi> So that the plain meaning of the Text ſeems to be this, <hi>Chriſt that was without all ſin, was made</hi> (that is, <hi>ordained of God</hi>) <hi>to be a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſin, that we might be made thereby righteous with the Goſpel-righteouſneſs:</hi> For that is the general meaning every where of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God:</hi> 'Tis oppoſed to <hi>mans</hi> righteouſneſs and the righteouſneſs of <hi>works,</hi> which is by the <hi>Law.</hi> If it be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed farther, and affirmed [That ſin it ſelf was <hi>ſo imputed</hi> to Chriſt, as that God in judgment did reckon him <hi>guilty</hi> and a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi>] (which the Scripture no where tells us, and 'tis great impiety to aſſert,) He is then excluded from all poſſibility of <hi>merit,</hi> for the ſuffered but what was his <hi>due,</hi> and ſo the whole of Chriſts <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is ſubverted. But he <hi>freely</hi> ſuffered the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of ſin that was infinitely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>deſert</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> and thereby redeemed us; <hi>became ſin,</hi> in that ſenſe, <hi>that ſo we might be made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in him.</hi> Now by the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, ſometimes is meant in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the <hi>Perſonal righteouſneſs of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:64072:39"/>who was <hi>God-Man,</hi> and ſometimes the <hi>righteouſneſs of Faith, that</hi> righteouſneſs that faith is accounted for, and which in the Goſpel is conditionally required of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſaved perſon: And this is ſo called, becauſe 'tis a righteouſneſs of Gods <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving,</hi> of Gods <hi>working,</hi> and of Gods <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting,</hi> in and through Chriſt, and for the ſake of his <hi>ſatisfaction.</hi> If you ask me for a Text to prove this latter, there are many: I will only inſtance in one: <hi>For they being ignorant of Gods righteouſneſs, and going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, have not ſubmitted themſelves to the righteouſneſs of God, Rom.</hi> 10.3. By the righteouſneſs of God here, is not meant the Perſonal righteouſneſs of the Mediator, but the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-righteouſneſs of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>believing</hi> by which we are Juſtified, in oppoſition to the Law, (which in the next <hi>ver.</hi> the Apoſtle tells them <hi>Chriſt was the end of, for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> by his ſatisfaction) ſo the Apoſtle expreſsly calls it in the 6th. <hi>ver. But the righteouſneſs which is of faith, ſpeaketh on this wiſe:</hi> And if you read to the 9th. <hi>ver.</hi> he there fully deſcribes this righteouſneſs of God, and tells you in other words what it is, <hi>That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64072:40"/>thine heart that God raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> And the whole Context puts it out of all doubt, that by <hi>their own righteouſneſs</hi> is meant the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law, which <hi>Moſes</hi> (the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayes in the 5th. <hi>ver.</hi> deſcribes in thoſe words. <hi>That the man that doth thoſe things ſhall live by them:</hi> And by the <hi>righteouſneſs of God,</hi> is meant <hi>the Goſpel righteouſneſs</hi> on <hi>our part to be performed,</hi> which the Apoſtle ſayes in the 6th. <hi>ver. Moſes</hi> does otherwiſe deſcribe; <hi>But the righteouſneſs which is of faith</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſpeaketh on this wiſe: Say not in thine heart who ſhall aſcend into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that is, to bring Chriſt down from above,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that is, the word of ſaith which we preach.</hi> If we take it in the firſt ſenſe, then the meaning of this Scripture, is this, Chriſt became a <hi>ſin-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> for us, and freely underwent the ſuffering and puniſhment due to ſin, <hi>that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> that is, that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt as <hi>Mediator</hi> in a way of <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> might be <hi>appropriated</hi> unto us: And as he underwent the <hi>conſequences</hi> of our ſin, ſo we might reap the <hi>effects</hi> of his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that we might be intereſted in his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64072:40"/>righteouſneſs, juſt as he was in our ſins. He ſuffered the <hi>penalty</hi> of our ſins, and we reap the <hi>fruit</hi> of his righteouſneſs, and ſo there is a mutual transferring of our ſins and Chriſts righteouſneſs in the <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>conſequences</hi> of both, but no otherwiſe. If we take it in the other ſenſe, (which is, I believe the ſenſe intended by the Apoſtle) then the meaning is, That Chriſt became a <hi>ſin-offering</hi> for us, that we might in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance thereof and as an <hi>effect</hi> of it, be made Righteouſneſs in the Goſpel-righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that is, that we by <hi>believing</hi> in him, might be <hi>accounted for righteous,</hi> and ſo <hi>accepted</hi> of God. The Apoſtle does not ſay, that we might be made <hi>His righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or that his righteouſneſs might be made <hi>perſonally ours,</hi> but <hi>that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him:</hi> And the phraſe <hi>In him,</hi> is not to be taken <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally</hi> and <hi>literally.</hi> For when we are ſaid to <hi>abide in him,</hi> 'tis to continue ſtedfaſt in the <hi>doctrine of the Goſpel; to walk in him,</hi> is to walk according to the rule of the Goſpel; to <hi>Sleep in him,</hi> is to die in the <hi>ſaith</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> to <hi>marry in the Lord,</hi> is to marry according to the <hi>rules</hi> he has <hi>preſcribed.</hi> So, to be Righteous <hi>in him,</hi> is to be righteous according to the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64072:41"/>
               <hi>rule</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to be righteous in the righteouſneſs of his <hi>procuring</hi> and <hi>appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi> When we read of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, we are not alwayes barely to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his <hi>natural Perſon,</hi> but to conſider him <hi>myſtically</hi> and <hi>politically,</hi> to conſider him circumſtanced as <hi>Head, King,</hi> and <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver</hi> to his <hi>Church;</hi> and upon that account his <hi>Name</hi> is often taken in a <hi>large</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive</hi> ſenſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another Text of Scripture much inſiſted on for the proof of Perſonal imputation, is,</hi> Rom. 5.19. For as by one mans diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one, ſhall many be made righteous.</p>
            <p>This text, upon due conſideration, will be found to make nothing at all for any ſuch Imputation and Transferring of righteouſneſs as is pretended. The Apoſtles ſcope from the 12th. <hi>ver.</hi> of that Chapter to the end of it, is evidently to prove theſe two things. Firſt, That as ſin came firſt into the world by <hi>Adam's diſobedience,</hi> and <hi>death</hi> by <hi>ſin,</hi> and did not only ſeize on him, but deſcended upon all his Poſterity, (even <hi>upon them that had not ſinned after the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64072:41"/>of</hi> Adam's <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> that is, againſt a <hi>Law promulgated,</hi> as he did) he begetting them in his image <hi>after</hi> his Fall, in his <hi>apoſtate</hi> ſtate, and not in his <hi>innocncy:</hi> So from Chriſts obedience and ſatisfaction for ſin, came <hi>righteouſneſs, life</hi> and <hi>ſalvation.</hi> In three things the Apoſtle makes the <hi>Feadſhip</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> and that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to run <hi>parallel.</hi> Firſt, As <hi>Adam</hi> had a <hi>publick</hi> Station, and ſtood ſo <hi>related</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> that he had power to involve <hi>them</hi> in his <hi>own condition:</hi> So had <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Secondly, the Effect of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> came upon <hi>all:</hi> The Effect of Chriſts obedience is ſo, comes upon <hi>all,</hi> that is, both upon <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> without diſtinction (which is the grand point the Apoſtle is all along making good;) Thirdly, the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> by his diſobedience was the general Author of <hi>death:</hi> Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> by obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, is the Great Introducer of <hi>life.</hi> And ſecondly, That there is <hi>not</hi> and <hi>exact equality</hi> and <hi>even proportion,</hi> between the Headſhip of Chriſt, and the Headſhip of <hi>Adam.</hi> So the Apoſtle tells us, in the 15 and 16 <hi>ver. But not as the offence, ſo alſo is the free gift: For if through the offence of One Many be dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, by one man Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64072:42"/>hath abounded unto many. And not as it was by one that ſinned, ſo is the gift I or the judgment was by one to condemnation, but the free gift is of many offences unto Juſtification.</hi> The Advantage lyes much on Chriſts ſide in the compariſon, and that in three reſpects. Firſt, Chriſts ſpiritual ſeed, Believers, are not ſo like him in <hi>degrees of holineſs,</hi> as <hi>Adams</hi> natural poſterity are like him in <hi>degrees of ſin:</hi> And yet Life reignes as triumphantly amongſt them, as Death did over the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of <hi>Adam.</hi> Secondly, it was <hi>one</hi> ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> that introduced Death: But Chriſts obedience, and the gift brought in by him, was not upon the occaſion of that, or any other <hi>one ſin,</hi> but of <hi>many,</hi> is the abundance of grace, and procures forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not only for <hi>that ſin,</hi> but for <hi>all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins</hi> whatſoever that have enſued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. And thirdly, there is a diſparity between <hi>Adam</hi> and Chriſt in this; (and the advantage lyes much on Chriſts ſide) That one ſin, one act of diſobedience was enough to <hi>condemn;</hi> But <hi>more</hi> the <hi>one act</hi> of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience was requiſite to procure our <hi>pardon.</hi> And ſo, although Chriſt do not ſave by his obedience <hi>ſo many</hi> as <hi>Adam</hi> condemned by his diſobedience; yet the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is much more potent then the firſt, becauſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64072:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>there is much more <hi>efficacy</hi> required in the <hi>Saving</hi> of <hi>One,</hi> then there was in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning</hi> of <hi>Many.</hi> As the reſtoring of <hi>One dead to life,</hi> is much <hi>harder</hi> then the <hi>deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the lives of <hi>many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, How <hi>by one mans diſobedience were many made ſinners?</hi> Why, <hi>Adam</hi> (who had all mankind vertually in himſelf) turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Rebel and an Apoſtate, his natural ſtate was thereby <hi>changed,</hi> his nature was attainted, and became ſinful, and ſo fell un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſentence of <hi>death;</hi> and that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the penalty threatned: <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt dye:</hi> Thy Natural ſtate ſhall be <hi>changed</hi> and ſubjected to <hi>death.</hi> And this falling out before he had propagated any of his kind, he begat all his poſterity in the ſame ſinful Mortal ſtate with himſelf: So the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>that in Adam all dye.</hi> That is, he becoming Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; all were ſo <hi>propagated,</hi> and Death reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon that account. So on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>by one mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>obedience many are made righteous.</hi> As all meer men ſinned in <hi>Adam,</hi> being all <hi>in him,</hi> and undergo the Effects of that ſin. So all Believers have <hi>virtually ſatisfied</hi> for ſin <hi>in Chriſt:</hi> By Chriſts obedience and ſatisfaction we come to be <hi>pardoned, accounted</hi> of as <hi>righteous,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:64072:43"/>and ſaved: But ſtill 'tis as an <hi>effect</hi> of Chriſts obedience that we come to be made righteous; for the Apoſtle does not ſay, <hi>In</hi> one mans obedience many ſhall be made righteous, but <hi>By</hi> one mans obedience (as a conſequent and Effect of it) many ſhall be made righteous. As the <hi>effect</hi> of one mans diſobedience, many come to be ſhapen in iniquity and brought forth in a ſinful condemned nature, ſo as by the Effect of one mans obedience, many come to be new born, and brought forth in a righteous and a ſaving ſfate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A third Text inſiſted on, is that in the</hi> 3d. chap. <hi>to the</hi> Philip. ver. 9. And be found in him, not having mine own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs which is of God by faith.</p>
            <p>To this Text a ſhort Anſwer will ſuffice. No more is requiſite then to read from the 4. <hi>v.</hi> where the Apoſtle is diſcourſing of his Attainments under the Law. <hi>Though I might</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>have confidence alſo in the fleſh, if any other man thinketh he hath whereof he might truſt in the fleſh, I more, circumciſed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64072:43"/>the eighth day,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo he goes on: And in the <hi>7th. ver. But what things were gain to me, thoſe I counted loſs for Chriſt, yea doubtleſs I count all things but loſs for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſs of all things, and do count them but dung that I may win Chriſt, and be found in him, not having mine own righteouſneſs which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs which is of God by faith.</hi> By which it is as plain as words can make it, That the righteouſneſs he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires <hi>Not</hi> to be found in, was <hi>his own,</hi> as he was a <hi>Jew</hi> and a <hi>Phariſee.</hi> And to be found in Chriſt, was no more then to be found <hi>ingraffed by Faith</hi> into the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> to be found in that righteouſneſs which is of God by faith, which is the <hi>Goſpel-righteouſneſs.</hi> No ſober minded man can imagine the Apoſtle did not deſire to be found in Goſpel-righteouſneſs, or that by his own righteouſneſs he meant <hi>that:</hi> For 'tis that alone can intitle us to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſts righteouſneſs; And he himſelf every where ſo earneſtly preſſeth men to ſtrive for it as indiſpenſably neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation, and rejoyeeth in it, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us what comfort he had took to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64072:44"/>ſider, <hi>that he had fought a good fight, had finiſhed his courſe, had kept the faith,</hi> and that as a reward of ſo doing, <hi>a crown of life was laid up for him in Heaven.</hi> Nor is there any one paſſage of St. <hi>Pauls Epiſtles</hi> againſt <hi>works,</hi> but 'tis very plain from the context, he intends the <hi>works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and no other: For, as he oppoſeth <hi>faith</hi> to <hi>works;</hi> ſo he alſo oppoſeth <hi>faith with Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-obedience</hi> to <hi>works.</hi> As <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.6. <hi>I or in Chriſt Jeſus neither circumciſion nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion availeth any thing, but ſaith that worketh by love,</hi> or, <hi>that is wrought and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by love:</hi> For ſo it is beſt rendered; and ſometimes oppoſeth <hi>evangelical obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, alone</hi> to the <hi>works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> as <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but a new Creature.</hi> And in the 1ſt. of <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Circumciſion is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion</hi> is <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the keeping the commands of God;</hi> where, by the <hi>commands of God,</hi> is meant the <hi>Law of the Goſpel.</hi> And Circumciſion (as 'tis often in other places) is put for the <hi>whole Law:</hi> For whoſoever was circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, the Apoſtle declares <hi>he was obliged to the whole Law.</hi> By which it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that whenever St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh againſt <hi>Works,</hi> in the matter of Juſtification,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64072:44"/>'tis the works of the <hi>Law,</hi> and not of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> that he intends, and ſo he is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: For by the works of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> we come to have a right and title to <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> as appears <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his commandments, that they may have right to the tree of life.</hi> That <hi>Goſpel Works</hi> are never excluded, but are equally intereſted with faith in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Juſtification, will appear true beyond any good denyal by theſe two conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Firſt, That faith that is ſaid to juſtifie, and does only ſo, is a faith that worketh by love; which is in other words to ſay, 'tis a faith that worketh by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere obedience, and keeping all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God. Secondly, the promiſes of the Goſpel are as well made, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thereof equally annexed to our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel obedience, as they are to our faith, which plainly ſhews, that <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> are inſeparably conjoyn'd in this matter; and that <hi>faith</hi> is alwayes ſo to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as comprehenſive thereof, without it, 'tis dead, is but a Karkaſs of <hi>faith,</hi> and not ſuch a living <hi>faith</hi> as the <hi>Goſpel</hi> intends when it ſpeaks of a juſtifying <hi>faith.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:64072:45"/>
            <head>SECT. IV.</head>
            <p>I Proceed to the third and laſt inquiry, which is this, <hi>How, do we come to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the benefits of Juſtification before God, and arrive at a juſtified eſtate?</hi> To this the Scripture gives us a plain and ready An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; <hi>By peforming the Goſpel-Condition:</hi> For all the advantages that accrue to the world from Chriſts ſatisfaction are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, <hi>conditionally</hi> to us, and no man is actually juſtified till the <hi>condition</hi> be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed;</hi> For <hi>whom he called, them he juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> And upon that account it is, that we read in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> of being <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by our faith,</hi> of being <hi>juſtified by our words and works. Goſpel-faith</hi> and <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> being the <hi>condition</hi> required on our part to be performed, and upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of which we are <hi>juſtified,</hi> and come to give up our <hi>account</hi> with <hi>joy;</hi> at the great Judgement day men will be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and condemned upon their performing, or not performing the Goſpel condition, as we find by our Saviours own words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 35. That the Covenant of Grace is in the propoſal of it <hi>conditional,</hi> and that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64072:45"/>Chriſt, with all his ſaving benefits, is by the Goſpel offered to us upon <hi>terms,</hi> that we ſtand obliged perſonally to <hi>perform,</hi> there needs no other proof then our <hi>Saviours</hi> own <hi>ſummary words</hi> about that matter. <hi>He that believes ſhall be ſaved, he that believes not ſhall be damned.</hi> And we find <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 1. When God firſt propoſed the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace to <hi>Abraham,</hi> he annexed <hi>ſincere obedience</hi> to it as the condition of it. <hi>Walk before me, and be thou upright, and I will make a Covenant with thee.</hi> Nor do we find our Saviour ever encouraging any to <hi>come to him,</hi> but upon the <hi>termes</hi> of <hi>taking his yoke,</hi> and <hi>bearing his burden.</hi> And indeed the Goſpel is every where ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in this point, and ſo very many Texts do affirm it, that no man but one extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intoxicated with the <hi>phrenzy</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomianiſm,</hi> can deny it; and it were la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour loſt to prove it.</p>
            <p>Now in regard the whole Conditiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Goſpel is compriſed in <hi>believing,</hi> and in that one word <hi>Faith,</hi> upon which account we are ſo often ſaid to be <hi>juſtified by faith.</hi> 'Tis of great concern to arrive at the Scripture ſenſe of this <hi>word,</hi> and its intendment by it. And to me it appears very evident, That to be <hi>juſtified by faith</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:64072:46"/>in Scripture, is generally taken to be Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>upon the terms of Chriſtianity</hi> and the principles of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in oppoſition to Legal and Jewiſh Juſtification: And by <hi>faith</hi> is comprehended <hi>whatever the Goſpel requires of us in order to Justification.</hi> The Goſpel is ſtiled <hi>the Law of faith,</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is required of us by it, is called the <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two Extreams are with great caution to be avoided in our conceptions of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-faith.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We muſt not, on the one hand, imagine that by faith and believing is meant only in the Goſpel <hi>a bare Crediting of God,</hi> and giving our <hi>aſſent</hi> to the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and acquieſeng therein. For to be a Believer, and to be a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere practical Chriſtian, is all one in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſenſe; and When we are told, that <hi>He that believeth ſhall be ſaved,</hi> and are told in many other places by our Saviour, and the Apoſtles, <hi>that 'tis thoſe only that Obey him alſo, and keep his commandments, ſubduing their corrupt luſts and affections, and working out their own ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> that ſhall be <hi>ſaved;</hi> and are generally told by the Goſpel, <hi>that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſs no man ſhall ſee God:</hi> 'Tis a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64072:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>and neceſſary Inference, <hi>that all that, and whatever elſe is made conditionally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to a juſtified ſaving ſtate, and our continuance therein, muſt be compriz'd in Faith and Believing:</hi> Or elſe we ſhall make the Goſpel not to be Correſpondent with it ſelf. And indeed, Faith is never ſpoke of in Scripture as <hi>bare believing</hi> and <hi>aſſenting,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>acting,</hi> but as the grand <hi>principle of Action,</hi> and ſo it is in it ſelf: The power of Belief is ſuch, that often it works <hi>phyſically,</hi> and with great efficacy does it operate <hi>morally.</hi> In the 11th. to the <hi>Heb.</hi> the Apoſtle tells us All the great Actions of thoſe noble Worthyes he mentions done before by <hi>faith,</hi> God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not an object of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> ſince the world began. Since <hi>Abels</hi> time, the ſpring of all Religious and Godly <hi>actions,</hi> has been <hi>faith.</hi> But the world were never <hi>under the Law of faith</hi> till the <hi>Goſpel was publiſhed.</hi> That faith was nothing elſe, and contained no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing farther then a bare Aſſent to the Revelation of the Goſpel as <hi>true,</hi> was that groſs Deluſion that led ſo many aſide in the firſt publication of the Goſpel. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallly of St. <hi>Pauls Epiſtles:</hi> For the <hi>Gnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and others unlearned and unſtable, as we find by <hi>Hegeſyppus</hi> in <hi>Euſebius, wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64072:47"/>the Scriptures,</hi> and held, That barely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the truth of Chriſtianity, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it, was enough, without any thing farther done, to ſave a man. Againſt this it is, That both St. <hi>John</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi> ſo fully then wrote: And St. <hi>John</hi> tells us po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively, <hi>That he that Doth righteouſneſs is only truely righteous:</hi> And not he that <hi>reckons</hi> himſelf ſo without righteous Doing upon the ſcore of believing. And St. <hi>James</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſets himſelf to confute this dangerous Errour, and to prove theſe two things. Firſt, That Chriſtianity, Believed and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, will profit no man, unleſs the Ends of it be purſued and proſecuted. And ſecondly, That that Faith that the Scripture calls a Juſtifying faith, is an <hi>operative working</hi> faith, a Faith that includes in its nature a ſuitable <hi>acting</hi> and <hi>obedience.</hi> Speaking of <hi>Abrahams faith,</hi> and his <hi>Juſtification,</hi> which the Scripture makes to be the pattern of Goſpel-faith and Juſtification; and the one to run parallel with the other: And which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had made ſo much uſe of, to prove <hi>Juſtification by faith</hi> againſt the <hi>Jews: Seeſt thou</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>how faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect, and the Scripture was fulfilled which ſaith,</hi> Abraham <hi>believed God, and it was imputed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:64072:47"/>to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> Where 'tis as plainly expreſſed as by words it can be; That that <hi>faith</hi> that was accounted to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> for righteouſneſs, was ſuch a <hi>faith,</hi> as contained in the bowels of it a ſuitable <hi>obedience,</hi> and <hi>ſubjection</hi> to all Gods revealed will and pleaſure. <hi>By works</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>faith was made perfect.</hi> That is, <hi>faith</hi> was in order to <hi>action,</hi> and a ſuitable <hi>acting</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> in purſuance of it, was <hi>included</hi> in it, and was that, which when performed, did compleat and perfect it, and without which, <hi>faith</hi> is altogether <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect,</hi> and is not <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>faith</hi> as in the Scripture is ſaid to be <hi>accounted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> And therefore it was upon <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſuitable <hi>obedience</hi> in proſecution of his <hi>faith,</hi> by which the Scripture was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, when it ſayes, <hi>Araham believed God, and that belief was accounted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> By which it is plain, that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> faith was counted for righteouſneſs, with reference to that <hi>obedience</hi> that was virtually <hi>compriz'd in it,</hi> and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: And that his <hi>faith</hi> and his <hi>works</hi> wrought <hi>joyntly together</hi> to obtain the <hi>ſame end.</hi> And this is no way contradicted by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who tells us that <hi>Abraham was not juſtified by works:</hi> For, the works that St.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64072:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> means, are plainly ſuch as the <hi>Law</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, ſuch <hi>perfect ſinleſs</hi> works as would in ſtrict rules of Juſtice make the reward to be <hi>Debt:</hi> And therefore when he oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth faith to works, 'tis but in other words, to oppoſe the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to the <hi>Law.</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> buſineſs is to prove Juſtification in the way of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> in oppoſition to Juſtification by the <hi>works</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> his province is to prove, that the faith that does juſtifie us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, is not a bare naked <hi>Aſſent,</hi> but ſuch a faith as <hi>Abrahams</hi> was, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in it a ſuitable <hi>obedience.</hi> The one <hi>Apoſtle</hi> aſſerts in oppoſition to the <hi>Jews, Evangelical</hi> Juſtification againſt <hi>Legal,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the general term <hi>faith:</hi> The other <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,</hi> for the confutation of Heretical Chriſtians, <hi>explains</hi> that term; and tells us, it imports not only <hi>believing of God,</hi> but an <hi>obedient Acting</hi> in proſecution thereof. That the Apoſtles do very well agree with each in their Doctrine, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by ſuch a faith as was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>works,</hi> and not by <hi>faith only,</hi> according to St. <hi>James:</hi> And yet that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was juſtified by <hi>faith</hi> and not by <hi>works,</hi> according to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> may be this made to appear. Firſt, That <hi>Abrahams</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:64072:48"/>faith that was counted for righteouſneſs, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded</hi> his ſuitable <hi>obedience</hi> according to St. <hi>James,</hi> and that his <hi>works</hi> did <hi>compleat</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> his <hi>faith:</hi> And that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was thereby fulfilled, that tells us the Act of his Believing, was counted for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is plain from the ſtory it ſelf in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> which St. <hi>James</hi> quotes. Had not his Believing compriz d a ſuitable <hi>obedience,</hi> inſtead of being counted for Righteouſneſs, it would no doubt have been eſteemed of God, as it had indeed been a great piece of <hi>hypocriſy.</hi> For <hi>Abrahams</hi> upright walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was the terms upon which God at firſt propoſed to enter into a Covenant with him. Secondly, That <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>not</hi> juſtified by works, according to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> though his faith that was counted for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs included his obedience, is thus evident: St. <hi>Pauls</hi> buſineſs is to prove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> who came firſt under the Law of Circumciſion, and from whom they derived themſelves, (for it appears by their diſcourſes with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, when they cryed out, <hi>We have A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham to our Father,</hi> that they went no higher) was juſtified <hi>before</hi> he came under the Law of Circumciſion, before he was obliged to the <hi>oeconomie</hi> of the Law, upon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64072:49"/>
               <hi>Goſpel-principles</hi> (and ſo <hi>thoſe</hi> had the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence</hi> of <hi>legal,</hi> even in <hi>Abraham</hi> their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) upon the terms of another Covenant, the Condition of which was Faith, upon ſuch terms as both Jews and Gentiles were to be juſtified <hi>then</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> Upon which account the Scripture ſtiles him the common <hi>Father of all the faithful. Abrahant,</hi> before that faith of his that was accounted to him for Righteouſneſs, had lived for ſome time in <hi>Heathen Idolatry,</hi> and was a great ſinner, and ſo could not pretend to be juſtified by a <hi>ſinleſs perfection,</hi> which the Law required, and the Jews inſiſted on, and ſo not by works in that ſenſe: He was one of the <hi>ungodly</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of in 4th to the <hi>Rom.</hi> who had not Legal perfection, had not ſuch works to plead as would make the reward, in ſtrict rules Juſtice, to be of <hi>debt:</hi> His Juſtification was upon the very ſame <hi>terms</hi> that the <hi>Gentiles then</hi> might be juſtified upon, though they had lived in the groſſeſt Idolatry; and that was by <hi>believing</hi> the <hi>revelation of God in Chriſt, charging</hi> their courſe of <hi>life,</hi> and becoming <hi>obedient</hi> to what God ſhould <hi>require</hi> of them. In ſhort, <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience was not ſuch Righteouſneſs, as in its own nature, and by its own intrinſick
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64072:49"/>worth, would juſtifle any man from the guilt of all his ſin, and denominate him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly a Righteous perſon; for had it ſo been in it ſelf, it needed not any <hi>favour</hi> to have been <hi>accounted</hi> for Righteouſneſs: But God was pleaſed out of <hi>grace</hi> ſo to <hi>reckon</hi> and <hi>account</hi> it. <hi>Abraham</hi> having blelieved God about the promiſes of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> that was to ſpring out of his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by whom himſelf and all the world were to be ſaved, (for the ſum of all Gods converſe with <hi>Abraham</hi> was to ſhew him <hi>Chriſts day,</hi> and reveal to him the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that was to come by <hi>him</hi>) God was pleaſed to give the world an <hi>inſtance</hi> in his imputing that faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> to him for Righteouſneſs, how, and upon what terms men ſhould be ſaved by the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> when he did come! (in a word, what ſhould be the <hi>condition</hi> he would require of us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form by the Goſpel) that is, By <hi>believing</hi> the revelation of Chriſt, and <hi>acting</hi> ſuitably thereunto by a <hi>ſincere</hi> though <hi>imperfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:</hi> This God would <hi>impute</hi> and <hi>account</hi> for <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> This is all that he would require on our part conditionally to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: This ſhould conſtitute us righteous upon the terms of the <hi>New Covenant:</hi> This ſhould legally intitle us by the Goſpel to all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64072:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Advantages of Chriſt, and to a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous end juſtified ſtate; and this is ſo far from ſuch a Juſtification by <hi>works</hi> as the Jews reſted in, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſputes againſt, that 'tis a Juſtification that reſults wholly from <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>favour,</hi> is the Effect of <hi>Chriſts purchaſe,</hi> and of the <hi>terms</hi> of <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Covenant:</hi> And all merit, and all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that can be claimed out of <hi>debt,</hi> is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly excluded thereby. And thus the two <hi>Apoſtles</hi> appear perfectly <hi>agreed</hi> in their <hi>doctrine: Abraham</hi> was not juſtified upon terms of the Law and ſinleſs perfection, but he was juſtified as an <hi>ungodly perſon,</hi> one that had <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>failings</hi> about him, that needed <hi>forgiveneſs,</hi> was juſtified by <hi>faith</hi> in way of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> And that faith that juſtified <hi>Abraham</hi> then, and juſtifies every perſon under the Goſpel now, and is by the tenour thereof accounted for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is not a naked <hi>aſſent</hi> to the <hi>truth</hi> what God <hi>reveals,</hi> but ſuch a faith as implyes in its nature, and comprizeth a ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>obedience</hi> to all he requires of us. There is a wide difference (as much as there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the nature and terms of the two Covenants) between ſuch <hi>works</hi> as by an <hi>inherent</hi> vertue in themſelves conſtitute <hi>juſt,</hi> and ſo juſtifie from an <hi>innate perfection</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:64072:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>as to make the reward to be of <hi>debt,</hi> and ſuch <hi>works</hi> are in their own nature alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>imperfect</hi> and <hi>faulty,</hi> and are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only thorough <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>favour,</hi> and made but <hi>conditionally</hi> neceſſary to our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification <hi>another way. Works,</hi> 'tis true, there are in the caſe both wayes; but of very different natures, upon very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Accounts, and to very different Ends.</p>
            <p>Secondly, On the other hand, we muſt carefully avoid ſo to apprehend <hi>faith,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to comprehend all that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel requires of us to believe and practice, as if it had in it ſelf any <hi>juſtifying vertue,</hi> or were of any <hi>innate worth</hi> to acquit us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God from the guilt of ſins. The value of it is wholly from <hi>Gods gracious or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> as it is all the <hi>condition</hi> that is required on our part to be performed by the Law of grace. And it is <hi>not of our ſelves</hi> neither, but 'tis <hi>the gift</hi> and <hi>beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of God. We obtain the <hi>precious faith</hi> of the Goſpel (St. <hi>Peter</hi> tell us) <hi>through the righteouſneſs of God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Whenever we read of our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by faith, 'tis meant of our being ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the Goſpel way; and that is, by <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone <hi>meritoriouſly,</hi> and by what he has
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64072:51"/>done and ſuffered (for, the Apoſtle tells us, that <hi>God for Chriſts ſake hath freely forgiven us:</hi> Nothing has the leaſt <hi>meritorious</hi> inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in our forgiveneſs, but Chriſt, Grace, and free forgiveneſs, in Scripture, is ſtill op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to our <hi>merit</hi>) and by <hi>faith only,</hi> with reſpect to its <hi>conditional</hi> relation to <hi>him,</hi> and that <hi>Covenant</hi> which he hath purchaſed and proclaimed, and in the method where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we come to be actually pardoned and juſtified upon Believing. To think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, is to ſubvert the grand deſign of the whole Goſpel, which we are often told, is <hi>to declare Chriſts Righteouſneſs for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins,</hi> and to ſot forth him as a <hi>propitiation through faith in his blood:</hi> Faith is no part of the Propitiation, but 'tis he himſelf and his blood that is the Propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and faith but the <hi>conditional means</hi> by which we come to reap the fruit and benefit of it. The whole Fabrick of the Goſpel is bottom'd upon <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> made to the Juſtice of God on our behalf, upon a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Our Savior ſayes, <hi>he came down to lay down his life</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a ranſome for many;</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a price of redemption.</hi> We are every where in Scripture ſaid to be <hi>ranſom'd, redeem'd, purchas'd, bought with a price:</hi> And
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64072:51"/>that muſt needs be by a <hi>valuable conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion pay'd,</hi> and by <hi>ſatisfaction made.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us what that price of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is that was payed for us, and by which we were purchaſed and ranſomed; <hi>'twas not corruptible things,</hi> ſuch as <hi>gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> or any thing we had to offer to God, but 'twas <hi>with the precious blood of Chriſt as of a Lamb without ſpot.</hi> No works nor perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of our own could ever have reached this purchaſe, or ſo prevailed as to have been accepted for a ſatisfaction in this caſe: For then a Justifying Righteouſneſs might have ſubſequently reſulted from the Law of Works, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> denyes, and tells us expreſsly, <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.21. that it could not be that way, it could not come by the Law: For, had there been a poſſibility of it, he tells us, it ſhould ſo have been: That is, could men either pefectly have kept the Law, or have ſufficiently anſwered for the Breach of it <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> Righteouſneſs would have been that way, and Chriſt had not dyed, for his death had been then in vain.</p>
            <p>Two things ſtill may be remembred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Faith, by which we may receive ſome account of the uſe that is made by the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt</hi> of this word in Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:64072:52"/>
            <p>Firſt, By <hi>faith</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is often deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in oppoſition to the <hi>Law,</hi> and the whole of it ſignified thereby. And the Reaſon of this ſeems to be becauſe the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is in its nature a Revelation from God propoſed to our <hi>belief;</hi> and all that we are required by it to <hi>do,</hi> flowes naturally from what we are firſt obliged to <hi>believe. Belief</hi> is the ſpring of all Goſpel-<hi>obedience,</hi> and does in its nature comprize all other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-graces; they being at firſt produced, and ever after upheld and increaſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the tenour of the Goſpel and Gods peculiar Ordination therein, the whole <hi>condition</hi> required by it, is at the firſt virtually performed by the bare act of <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving,</hi> as the repreſentative of all other Graces, and root of univerſal obedience. 'Tis <hi>all</hi> that at the firſt is made conditional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to conſtitute a Juſtified ſtate, though to the after-continuance in it, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of every other grace is equally requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. He that ſincerly believes in Chriſt as he is propoſed, is truely in a Juſtified ſtate by ſuch an Act of Faith (and herein Faith hath the preference of all other Graces, in point of Juſtification) if we never live to perform any ſubſequent Act of Obedience: And the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:64072:52"/>of this, may be theſe two. Firſt, The grace of Faith has in its nature a Nearer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, wherein the Eſſentials of our Juſtification conſiſt, then any other Grace whatſoever: For all we can do with reference to <hi>that,</hi> and the neareſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach we can make to it, to receive the benefit and advantage of it, is to <hi>believe</hi> it, and to <hi>rely upon</hi> it. Secondly, A true and ſincere faith and belief of the Goſpel, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth and includeth a firm <hi>reſolution</hi> to <hi>act accordingly;</hi> that is, to purſue the Ends of that Faith in all ſuch acts of obedience as are ſubſequently required of us: And this God ſees virtually contained in the firſt Act of true Faith, and the <hi>ſeeds</hi> of all future ſincere perſevering obedience therein: And upon that account accepts thereof at firſt, as the performance of the <hi>whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> required by the Goſpel legally to intitle us to the priviledge of a Juſtified ſtate.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:64072:53"/>
            <head>SECT. V.</head>
            <p>ANd now the laſt thing propoſed to be inquired after, [How and upon what terms we come to arrive at the benefits of a Juſtified ſtate] having been thus reſolved; that we arrive thereunto by coming up to the terms propoſed by the Goſpel, and performing the condition therein required, which is briefly comprized by our Saviour in <hi>Believing:</hi> It will turn much to our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in this preſent Diſcuſſion, to inquire with ſome farther particularity, what is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> and <hi>comprehended therein!</hi> And of that, we may be much informed by the conſideration of theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>way</hi> and <hi>method</hi> that God takes to juſtifie a ſinner, being originated in the <hi>depths of his infinite Counſels,</hi> no way ever to be found out or diſcovered, but by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation;</hi> a great <hi>myſtery hid from ages,</hi> and a thing very <hi>incredible</hi> to a <hi>carnal mind,</hi> and no way ſuited to the corrupt Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Fleſh and Blood: God expects, in the firſt place, that we ſhould fully credit it; and firmly give our aſſent to its veracity:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:64072:53"/>And this is in it ſelf a very Righteous Act and ſo accounted of God, firmly to <hi>believe him</hi> in what he reveals to us. And herein the faith of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and that of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in whoſe ſteps we are bid to tread, do perfectly reſemble each other. For, he <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> God about diverſe things in their own nature very <hi>hard</hi> to be <hi>credited: He ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred not through unbelief, but hoped againſt hope,</hi> and ſtill relyed upon Gods <hi>veracity and all-ſufficiency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God requires of us, That he having revealed from Heaven ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and extraordinary way of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Salvation, ſo far out of our own compaſs and ſpan, as is the ſending of his Son to aſſume our nature, and in that nature to perfect and compleat all that concern'd our preſent und future welfare: He expects upon this, that we ſhould <hi>adore</hi> this Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>bow</hi> before it with the greateſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments we are capable of making, <hi>rely</hi> upon it, <hi>acquieſce</hi> in it; and be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſilenced to all attempts our own Wiſdom can ſuggeſt to us about this matter. And herein the faith of the Goſpel, anſwers punctually to that of <hi>Abraham:</hi> For, he wholly quitted all thoſe methods carnal and corrupted reaſon would have directed him
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64072:54"/>to. <hi>He left his Country and his fathers houſe, and went he knew not whither.</hi> In a word, he forſook the conduct of his own wiſdom, Believed whatever God told him, Did all he bad him, and Went whitherſoever he called him, whatever Difficulties appeared to himſelf, and whatever Cenſures he lay expoſed to from others in his ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God and the Mediator require of us, that we ſhould become Obedient to a New Recovering Law of Grace, as the <hi>condition</hi> of our <hi>Pardon</hi> and Juſtification: In a word, That we ſhould ſubject our ſelves to all the precepts of the Goſpel: For, Chriſt as Mediator erects a Kingdom; His exaltation is to be a <hi>Prince,</hi> as well as a <hi>Saviour;</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> in being a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and whoſoever will be <hi>ſaved</hi> by him, muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> muſt ſubmit to the <hi>regiment</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>ſubject</hi> himſelf to his <hi>Laws.</hi> And herein the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and the faith of every <hi>Believer,</hi> anſwer one to another, as face anſwereth face in a glaſs: For <hi>Abrahams</hi> Juſtification was upon performance of the <hi>terms</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> of the New Covenant. The Apoſtle proves he was <hi>juſtified by faith,</hi> which was to be juſtified upon the terms of <hi>another Covenant,</hi> and not that of the Law: For <hi>the law is not of faith,</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:64072:54"/>nor faith of the Law, there was no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all between <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>law,</hi> the <hi>law</hi> made no promiſe to <hi>faith,</hi> the promiſes of the <hi>law</hi> were to perfect <hi>obedience.</hi> And as the Apoſtle with convincing evidence ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth againſt the Jews <hi>Abraham was juſtified by a faith he had before he was circumciſed,</hi> or had any thing to do with the Law. And that faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> was more then a bare fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>aſſent</hi> to what God revealed to him: 'Twas ſuch a faith as put him upon <hi>Action,</hi> and approved its own truth by a ſuitable <hi>obedience:</hi> And of this we are ſufficiently informed by the Story it ſelf in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and by St. <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Comment</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p>Some things there are to be remarked in this Diſpoſal of God, that highly exalt his Wiſdom, Holineſs and Juſtice: And ſome things that to a very ſtupendious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree do magniſie his Mercy.</p>
            <p>Firſt, How is the Wiſdom, Holineſs and Juſtice of God, made very tranſparent by ſuch a diſpenſing Pardon and Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as this! How ſuitable is this method to <hi>himſelf!</hi> He forgives not as the Greateſt of men often do, and think it an effect of the moſt <hi>ſupream ſoveraignty</hi> ſo to do; as if in forgiveneſs nothing were to be done, but ſingly to exerciſe an act of <hi>ſoveraignty.</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:64072:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>But he forgives like the <hi>Lord our Maker:</hi> That eternal <hi>Jehovah</hi> who is <hi>wonderful in counſel, and excellent in working,</hi> with whom are inherent infinite Attributes, none of which in the leaſt can be Denyed, or in the leaſt Oppoſe, or Contradict each other; He proceeds in all he does in methods chalk'd out by his infinite Wiſdom, wherein they are all attempered together, and do after an admirable manner <hi>harmonize</hi> each with other. He annexeth ſuch <hi>conditions</hi> to his <hi>forgiveneſs,</hi> as no way leſſen the <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>bounty</hi> of it, and yet at the ſame time record his immutable <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>greateſt righteouſneſs</hi> that ever was extant, the <hi>holyeſt</hi> ſtate of man that he is capable of in his lapſed condition, is introduced by the <hi>goſpel</hi> and the precepts thereof; and the greateſt <hi>homage</hi> from Earth to Heaven that can be: And yet all fleſh put to ſilence in the performance of it. We ſtand juſtified at Gods Bar in a way of Gods <hi>providing</hi> and <hi>contriving;</hi> and we perform the Condition required of us ſolely by the power of his <hi>grace freely conferred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us:</hi> The glory of all redounds to God alone. No Reward can be of Debt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for all the Rewards of the Goſpel are but Gods <hi>gracious remunerations of his own
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64072:55"/>gifts and graces. Free grace,</hi> and <hi>Divine bounty</hi> is the Root that bears all; nor can there be any boaſting againſt that Root. The holieſt man that lives upon earth has the greateſt occaſion, as having received moſt, to abaſe himſelf, and lie loweſt in the duſt before God in the Senſe thereof, in his beſt performances.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By this method of forgiving, theſe two great Ends are attained. Firſt, Gods ſolemn <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>diſlike</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> is made very evident. He ſave no man <hi>in</hi> his ſin, but <hi>from</hi> his ſin. Whom he <hi>juſtifies,</hi> he <hi>ſanctifies:</hi> No mans ſin is ſo forgiven, as that the leaſt <hi>allowance</hi> is vouchſafed to it. How impoſſible were if for God openly to tolerate a Rebellion (as all ſin is, for 'tis a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to ſome Law) againſt himſelf! How inconſiſtent were it with his Holineſs and his Soveraignty! By the Conditions God has annexed to his Forgiveneſs,
'twill evidently appear before men and Angels, what a Contrariety and Oppoſition there is in God to all ſin, reſulting from the eſſential Purity of his nature: And that none but ſuch as are <hi>ſanctified</hi> can be <hi>accepted</hi> of him. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, By the performance of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions we are made <hi>meet</hi> for Glory, 'tis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Heaven <hi>gradually.</hi> 'Tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:64072:56"/>without <hi>holineſs</hi> to ſee <hi>God.</hi> And 'tis our great happineſs, that ſo great a ſtreſs is laid upon our attaining to it: That we are under ſo ſolemn an <hi>obligement</hi> to our greateſt <hi>Intereſt.</hi> Doubtleſs, the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual way to introduce <hi>ſanctity,</hi> was to make it <hi>conditionally neceſſary</hi> to our <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication:</hi> and to oblige us to forſake our ſins upon our utmoſt Peril, and greateſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</p>
            <p>Some things there are alſo obſervable in this Goſpel method, of Pardon, by which the <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> of God are made great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evident, and appear in their higheſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Precepts of this new recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Law of Grace, the commands of the Goſpel; our obedience to which is made conditionally neceſſary to a juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtate: They are ſuch as appear to be wholly calculated for our <hi>advantage</hi> and <hi>welfare. The yoke of Chriſt,
'tis</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a gracious, benigne, bountiful yoke, and his burden is a light burden. His commands are in no ſort Grievous</hi> to any man truly and rationally informed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of his own welfare. God has not <hi>arbitrarily</hi> commanded us, as he might do, (for, we owe him all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable ſubjection,) but ſingly oblig'd us
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64072:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſuch precepts as are in their own nature abſolutely neceſſary to our preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture welfare. In ſhort, he has only bid us live a <hi>ſober, righteous, religious life here,</hi> ſuch as is rationally Beſt for our ſelves, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and be gradually preparing for thoſe Eternal fruitions that are to come. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever comes ſhort of Heaven by not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Goſpel-condition, denyes his own preſent as well as future Intereſt: And 'twill be a black Reflection hereafter to conſider, That whatever brought us to a ſtate of Miſery in the Next world, made us alſo unhappy in This: That God requited no more of us to qualifie us for future Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity; Then that we would live wiſely and profitably to our ſelves, and uſefully to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers here.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whatever is by the Goſpel Conditionally required of us, is all freely and fully <hi>given</hi> to us. Faith at firſt, and every other Grace in purſuance of it, is <hi>the gift of God.</hi> Whatever we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do, as a peculiar and principle effect of Chriſts purchaſe by the Law of Grace, we receive a power to perform. The Holy Ghoſt upon Chriſts aſcenſion was eminently ſent from Heaven for that very purpoſe, and will not ceaſe in his operations,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64072:57"/>till all the members of Chriſts Body are fully inabled to perform the Whole of what the Goſpel requires at their hands: This is an apparent Effect of the higheſt Grace and Goodneſs, and renders Chriſt as free a Gift to the World, as if <hi>no Condition</hi> had been annexed to the propoſal of him, ſince the power of performing all is Freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon us, when from the Greatneſs, Holineſs, and Juſtice of God, and our own preſent and future welfare, it became ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that ſuch holy Conditions there ſhould be. God in his boundleſs Grace, undertakes in Chriſt, and obliges himſelf by his Covenant to furniſh us with ability for their utmoſt performance. By which method the whole will appear perfectly made up of <hi>free grace.</hi> The Satisfaction <hi>contriv'd, provided, accepted,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition <hi>performed:</hi> And every ſaved perſon will appear <hi>righteous</hi> both before God and the world, and 'twill be very apparently <hi>a righteous thing with God</hi> to bring ſuch unto Glory, who have <hi>Chriſts righteousſneſs</hi> by way of <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and <hi>compenſation,</hi> to anſwer for them with reſpect to the <hi>Law,</hi> and their own <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> (though imperfect) <hi>obedience</hi> to anſwer the terms of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, This gracious recovering Law
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:64072:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Mediator; 'Tis not given as God gave the firſt Law to <hi>Adam,</hi> and as he after gave the Law upon <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>exact</hi> and <hi>punctual obedience in every circumſtance</hi> of it upon the greateſt penalty: But 'tis given from the hand of a <hi>Mediator</hi> upon far more <hi>gentle</hi> and <hi>mitigated terms.</hi> 'Tis required by it, that we be deeply and thoroughly <hi>ſenſible</hi> of the <hi>ill</hi> of our former ſtate and converſation, while <hi>without God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt in the world, and ſtrangers to this grace of Goſpel,</hi> and of our utter inability to procure acceptance with God any <hi>other way:</hi> be rationally ſatisfied of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that life the Goſpel calls us unto, of the glorious reward that will enſue; And ſo make a ſolemn <hi>choice</hi> of it to our ſelves, and ſincerely reſolve, as men of Truth and Fidelity ought, ſtrenuouſly to endeavour to attain to it, to live in the practice of every duty the Goſpel annexes to our ſtate and condition, and to depart from every Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-ſin. This conviction and reſolution the Goſpel makes indiſpenſibly neceſſary, and 'tis compriz'd in all ſincere and true Faith. But 'tis thus <hi>qualified</hi> for the advantage of an offender; That that which conſtitutes and preſerves the union between Chriſt and a Believer, the <hi>thred</hi> that <hi>tyes</hi> a man
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64072:58"/>to Chriſt (as I may ſo expreſs it) in the whole performance of the Goſpel-condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is <hi>ſincerity of Intention and endeavour,</hi> (and what could the <hi>Great God</hi> require, and accept <hi>leſs</hi> from the hand of an <hi>Apoſtate Creature</hi>) and not <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>Action:</hi> And this <hi>ſincerity</hi> too reckon'd as much to our <hi>advantage</hi> as poſſible may be; That is, Whatever can, upon the utmoſt <hi>allowances,</hi> be truly ſo called, ſhall be ſo <hi>reputed:</hi> And he that can enter a juſt claim to the <hi>loweſt degree of ſincerity,</hi> that is, when all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities that can accompany ſincerity, and not overwhelm and extinguiſh it, that can conſiſt with its denomination ſo to be, are admitted, ſhall yet be accounted a <hi>ſincere man,</hi> and numbred amongſt thoſe that are <hi>truly ſo.</hi> Till this thred of <hi>ſincerity</hi> be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>broke,</hi> the union between Chriſt and a Believer is never Diſſolved, but he ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in a juſtified ſtate before God. Though a man ſin often through infirmity, and ſtrength of Temptation, (and the beſt men ſo ſin very often) if his <hi>Reſolution</hi> abide firm and ſincere for obedience to Chriſt, and holy living, he is ſtill reckoned to perform the Goſpel-condition, and abide in a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſtate: Such a man is in the firſt Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Goſpel-forgiveneſs. But if a man
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64072:58"/>through the power and prevalency of his Luſts, and the violent impetuous aſſaults of temptation, have an invaſion made upon his ſincerity, that is, that a man often fails in point of <hi>ſincerity,</hi> ſins againſt his own Light, and his Reſolutions, and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, repeats this again and again; does it often, (for, ſuch is mans apoſtate ſtate by his Fall, ſo fertile is it of all ſort of ſin, that if Chriſt in this new Law had not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered our frame, and remembred with infinite compaſſion what we are, and ſo dealt with us, we had ſtill come ſhort of happineſs) yet, if ſuch a man by the ſtrength and efficacy of grace, renew himſelf again by continued acts of Repentance, revive and re-inforce his reſolutions, return back to his firſt ſtated ſincerity, be in his ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and moſt Deliberate choice ſtill for Chriſt, and Obedience to his Laws, (for Chriſt will not ſinally judge of us by our <hi>paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> choice, but by our <hi>rational</hi> choice) and ſo carry himſelf upon the whole matter, that Chriſt is not <hi>depoſed</hi> his ſoul, but ſtill continues his <hi>Government</hi> there, if Satan and the Fleſh prevail but by <hi>ſits,</hi> and are ſtill diſpoſſeſſed by an <hi>habitual ſincerity;</hi> If a man be always either at the preſent, or upon ſecond, and after reviews, full of deep
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:64072:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>and heart-affecting trouble, and ſorrow, whenever he ſo miſcarryes, and the fixed ſtate, acquieſcency, and reſt of his ſoul is in living to Chriſt in a ſincere obedience to his Laws, and his rational and moſt undiſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed choice is to do; in ſhort, if he never comes to be bowed down, and ſubjected to <hi>pregnant hypocriſy,</hi> even in all caſes of this nature, the Scripture gives us good ground to believe, that Chriſt, and his ſaving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits are to be had, Juſtification before God attained, and future glory poſſeſſed (upon ſuch gracious principles of condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention, is this New Law of the Goſpel erected.) Though it muſt be withall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, that ſins of this nature, ſins tinctur'd with <hi>inſincerity,</hi> are of all under the Goſpel the moſt dangerous, border moſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a breach of the Condition required, are the moſt deſtructive to our preſent Peace and Comfort, the moſt productive of any of temporal and ſpiritual Judgements in this life: And when they arrive to ſuch a degree, that the whole of a mans condition truly and evenly conſidered, (for, we ſhall all be weighed in the perfect Ballance of Gods righteous judgement) they turn the Scale againſt ſincerity; are the more Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Prevailing part, they are perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64072:59"/>
               <hi>Ruinous,</hi> a <hi>Non-performance</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel-condition,</hi> is returned upon us, and no ſuch man will ever have the <hi>advantages</hi> of <hi>Chriſts ſatisfaction</hi> accounted to him, let him have made never ſo great a progreſs in all other Goſpel attainments.</p>
            <p>Two Fundamental Failures there are in reference to the Conditions required by the Goſpel, upon the performance of which, begun, and continued, we come to be prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and finally juſtified. Firſt, When men <hi>wholly reject the Goſpel,</hi> or with a careleſs, unconcern'd, unactive Indifferency, (which comes, in the effects, all to one) barely <hi>aſſent</hi> to its <hi>veracity,</hi> but never proſecute the Ends of it: And ſecondly, when men prove <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>perfidious</hi> in that ſubjection and obedience Chriſt requires from them in a Chriſtian courſe. Chriſt will anſwer for no man that will not receive him when offer'd as worthy of all acceptation, and as an ineſtimable Jewel of an Infinite va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, or that does not ſincerely intend to obey his Laws, and act ſuitably to ſuch an intention. 'Twere a mean and unworthy conception of our Saviour, to imagine he ſhould account the Precious Effects of his moſt Precious Blood to any man that would not be throughly ſenſible of that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64072:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſin, and rebellion againſt the Higheſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign that occaſioned his ſufferings, and to expiate which he became a <hi>ſin offering,</hi> and was <hi>ſacrificed;</hi> and in the moſt ſincere and ſolemn manner reſolve for the future, as the worſt of all <hi>ills,</hi> (the Wound of Life, the Sting of Death, and tormenting Plague to Eternity) to avoid it: And eſpecially, that ſhould pretend to do, and yet lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, and prove falſe in ſo gracious a Covenant. In a word, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing keeps men from the good things of the Goſpel, the bleſſedneſs of a juſtified ſtate, but a poſitive Refuſal of Chriſt, (or a ſloathful, careleſs, unconcern'd neglect of him, (which comes in effect all to one) or a prevailing unconquered falſeneſs in the courſe of Goſpel-obedience, and that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to his Laws which Chriſt requires from us. And who can imagine that ſuch a <hi>Saviour</hi> as our Lord is, who is <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> after a ſtupendious manner united, ſhould be provided by the Almighty for any perſons in either reſpect ſo qualified?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:64072:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>SECT. VI.</head>
            <p>FRom the conſideration of all theſe things, divers material Queſtions do naturally reſult; To which a due <hi>Anſwer</hi> ought to be given.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This Queſtion will be asked: <hi>Does not this diminiſh the</hi> Grace <hi>of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and leſſen the</hi> free <hi>donation of Chriſt, to ſay he is offer'd</hi> conditionally, <hi>and that no man can be juſtified by him but upon</hi> terms <hi>to be perform'd by</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it appear in truth ſo to be, that no man can be ſaved by Chriſt, nor be ſaid in the Goſpel-Senſe to love him, that does not keep his Commands, if we go further in this matter, then to thoſe Limitations the Goſpel evidently puts upon it ſelf; then this Objection ought not to be made: For, Gods pleaſure is the rule of his own Grace. That the Goſpel is Conditional, is apparent beyond denyal: <hi>If we live after the fleſh,</hi> we are told, <hi>we ſhall</hi> certainly <hi>dye,</hi> and <hi>if we mortifie the deeds of the body, we ſhall live: If
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64072:61"/>we overcome, we ſhall have the Crown,</hi> if we do not we ſhall <hi>loſe the Reward:</hi> And <hi>If we faint,</hi> we are told, <hi>we ſhall not reap:</hi>
'Tis <hi>he that holds out to the End,</hi> in a Chriſtian courſe, <hi>that ſhall be ſaved,</hi> And is not this all <hi>Conditional?</hi> And this Conditionality of the Goſpel, the offer of Chriſt upon <hi>terms,</hi> does no way Extenuate the grace and mercy of God in the free donation of Chriſt: <hi>We are juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt,</hi> though we are juſtified <hi>conditionally</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> and that Faith includes all <hi>Goſpel-obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> and the <hi>whole duty</hi> of a Chriſtian. Our Salvation is intirely purchaſed by <hi>Chriſts blood,</hi> and an ability to perform every Condition required of us, is <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed</hi> for us, and by him <hi>freely</hi> conferr'd upon us. So that he, as a gift of ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable value and bounty from Heaven, is a <hi>ſpring of all Grace,</hi> and freely ſupplies us with what ever we ſtand in need of: And the propoſal of him to the world upon <hi>terms</hi> and <hi>conditions,</hi> is but that <hi>method</hi> the <hi>only wiſe God</hi> has ſeen fit to make uſe of, in the accompliſhment of ſo glorious a work of <hi>Grace,</hi> and ſo <hi>free</hi> a <hi>Redemption,</hi> as that which tended moſt to his own <hi>glory;</hi> and will appear at laſt to be eminently <hi>beſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64072:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>for us:</hi> For, 'tis but firſt to <hi>oblige</hi> us, and then to <hi>inable</hi> us to be <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>like Himſelf,</hi> in whoſe <hi>image</hi> lyes the perfection of all <hi>Happineſs.</hi> 'Tis but to ſave us here <hi>in part,</hi> and that we might <hi>gradually</hi> poſſeſs that <hi>Gift of God, which is eternal life through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. Secondly, <hi>By this Doctrine, how can we ever come to know we are carefully and compleatly Juſtified, till we have fully perform'd and accompliſhed</hi> all the conditions <hi>made requiſite to a juſtified ſtate? That is, how can we, upon good ground be aſſured of our Juſtification till our</hi> faith <hi>and</hi> obedience be <hi>conſummuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Which is not till we dye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Every man is then Actually juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the Goſpel-Law, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly ſo, <hi>when he believes in the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt with all his heart.</hi> Becauſe no more is at the <hi>firſt</hi> required Legally to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a juſtified ſtate. But Juſtification is a <hi>continued</hi> act of God; and the <hi>conſtant</hi> performance of all thoſe duties which a ſincere reception of Chriſt as he is offered in the Goſpel, implyes, are indiſpenſibly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the continuance of it. 'Tis in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:64072:62"/>this caſe, as 'tis in <hi>Marriage:</hi> A Marriage is perfected by a <hi>mutual conſent;</hi> But the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of <hi>all matrimonial duties is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed</hi> in that conſent: The Marriage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues valid till ſomwhat be done (as 'tis very poſſible there may be) that does vertually <hi>Null</hi> and <hi>Revoke</hi> ſuch conſent, and what was implyed therein, and does <hi>ex natura rei,</hi> Diſſolve, the <hi>Vinculum matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij.</hi>
'Tis plain the Apoſtles did look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch as declared a firm aſſent to the Goſpel, and a ſincere and hearty reception of Chriſt as he is there propoſed, <hi>to be in Chriſt:</hi> That is, to be in a Juſtified ſaved ſtate, admitted them to all Goſpel-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and never eſteemed them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, till by their Lives, or Profeſſions, they contradicted, and denyed what by ſuch a faith and conſent they had before affirmed, and thereby Apoſtatized from it: And of ſuch <hi>tergiverſation</hi> the Goſpel every where warns men; <hi>That they ſhould take heed of an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Corinthians: I am jealous over you</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>with a godly jealouſie, for I have eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you to one husband, that I may preſent you as a chaſte Virgin to Chriſt: But I fear leaſt by any means as the ſerpent beguiled</hi> Eve
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64072:62"/>
               <hi>through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt:</hi> Whoever avows the faith of the Goſpel, and a ſincere cloſure with Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Terms thereof, and does after fall into an open <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt him, and lives in an allowed diſobedience to his Laws, ſuch a man is, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of an <hi>Heretick,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a man condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by himſelf:</hi> For he that in his Baptiſm, and at his firſt admiſſion into the Chriſtian-Church, had made a ſolemn Profeſſion of the true Chriſtian Doctrine, and did after degenerate into Corrupt and Heretical Opinions, contrary and deſtructive to it; paſſed <hi>ſentence</hi> upon <hi>himſelf.</hi> So, He that declares to cloſe with Chriſt as a Prince and a Saviour, which ſuppoſeth a general ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to all the Laws of his Kingdom, and ſhall after Indulge himſelf in a courſe of open diſobedience, and chooſe a continued practice of ſin againſt that grand fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Law of Chriſt: That, <hi>he that names his name, muſt depart from iniquity;</hi> gives Judgment againſt himſelf in this caſe, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns Chriſt and the Goſpel, Diſſolves the Relation that ſeem'd to be between them, and publickly retracts what he before obliged himſelf to: So that a man is at the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64072:63"/>firſt actually and legally according to the tenor of the Goſpel juſtified by a true and ſincere Faith: But a conſtant proſecution of ſuch a faith in all its proper Ends and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies by an univerſal ſubmiſſion to all the Laws of Chriſts Kingdom, is of abſolute neceſſity to our <hi>continuance</hi> in a Juſtified ſtate.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>Do not divers Scriptures in the New Teſtament ſeem to eſtabliſh Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſolely upon</hi> believing, <hi>and upon</hi> Faith, <hi>only as an</hi> inſtrument receiving, <hi>and no more, in oppoſition to all ſort of</hi> working? <hi>Eſpecially that Text,</hi> Rom. 4.5. But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, his faith is counted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are ſaid to be juſtified in the New Teſtament by faith alone, upon theſe three accounts. Firſt, as faith intends the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Law</hi> and the principles of <hi>Judaiſme.</hi> Secondly, As 'tis a <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive</hi> word for all that the Goſpel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires at our hands: For, by Believing in Chriſt, the Scripture intends ſuch a cloſure
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64072:63"/>with him, as receives him in all his offices, and ſujects us to all thoſe obligations, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prince and Saviour he thinks fit by the Goſpel to lay upon us: And upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to <hi>Believe,</hi> and to <hi>obey,</hi> are often in Scripture put one for the other promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo are <hi>unbelief</hi> and <hi>diſobedience.</hi> All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and ſubjection to Chriſt is origina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in, and flows from our Belief of that Revelation God makes to us of him, and is naturally implyed, and compriz'd in it: And ſo it has by Gods appointment the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and preferrence of all other Graces in point of Juſtification, and we do not find any other grace ſo related to Juſtification as this. And upon that account it is, that we are not ſaid in Scripture to be juſtified by <hi>repentance,</hi> or by <hi>love,</hi> or any other ſingle grace, but only by <hi>Faith,</hi> as compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of all the reſt. And thirdly, becauſe we are actually brought into a juſtified ſtate at firſt, ſolely by <hi>Faith</hi> without the actual exerciſe of any other grace: The very act of ſincere believing, by Gods peculiar and gracious ordination, intitles us to Chriſt, and all his Benefits: And the reaſon of that Ordination is evidently this; That who ever believes in Chriſt, receives him as he is by God propoſed; and whoever does ſo,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64072:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>obliges himſelf therey to all the duties of Chriſtianity. But upon no one of theſe accounts can Faith be ſaid to juſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> barely as an <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> but as 'tis compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive and productive of all other Goſpel-duties; and by the ſubſequent performance of them, Faith (as St. <hi>James</hi> tells us) is <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</hi> 'Twas the fear many good men had of intereſting any Works, or any thing of our own Juſtification, and Ecclipſing free grace thereby, that made them that they would neither allow Faith to be a <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> nor a <hi>work,</hi> (When they ought to have conſidered, that Goſpel works are never oppoſed to Grace, nor can any thing done by Divine aſſiſtance be ſo; and when the Apoſtle oppoſeth Works to Grace, he means ſuch Works as are inconſiſtent with Grace, and ſo juſtifie by their merit, as to put us out of need of Grace, and render it uſeleſs) but invented that unſcriptural notion of its <hi>inſtrumentality</hi> (of no other uſe, but to make way for <hi>metaphyſical ſubtilties,</hi> and to <hi>obſcure</hi> a <hi>plain point</hi>) when indeed Faith is both a <hi>work,</hi> and a <hi>condition.</hi> Firſt, 'Tis a <hi>work;</hi> ſo our Saviour himſelf calls it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.29. <hi>This is the work of God that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> Indeed, 'tis the chiefeſt part of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical obedience, the greateſt work
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:64072:64"/>the Goſpel requires at our hands, and that which produceth all other; and
'tis plainly made as ſuch, every where in Scripture the <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>New Law,</hi> and that which it requires on our part to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, in order to our Juſtification and Salvation. And ſo the Apoſtle declares when he ſayes, <hi>We have believed that we might be juſtified:</hi> That is, We have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the <hi>Condition</hi> required by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in order to Juſtification, that ſo we might be juſtified thereby upon the <hi>terms</hi> thereof: And for that reaſon, as 'tis the <hi>Condition</hi> of the New Law, 'tis <hi>accounted for Righteouſneſs.</hi> And ſo when God juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>Abraham</hi> upon the terms of the New Covenant, <hi>his Faith</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>accounted for Righteouſneſs,</hi> becauſe it was the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the <hi>Condition</hi> thereof: And God was pleaſed to give an Inſtance in him what was to be the Condition of it, which was, a ſincere <hi>Faith,</hi> including a ſuitable <hi>obedience:</hi> So far different was <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith in its Nature, and ſo far is all true Goſpel-Faith from that <hi>Idea</hi> ſome men frame of it, who aſcribe no more to it then a Bare naked notional <hi>inſtrumentality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is there one Text in all the New Teſtament that excludes Goſpel-<hi>Works, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64072:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>obedience</hi> from being <hi>Conditionally neceſſary</hi> to our Juſtification and Salvation, but they are univerſally made ſo, as has been proved before: For, Whatever is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to conſtitute a man a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, is conditionally neceſſary to his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification; and no man can be intereſted in the Salvation purchaſed by Chriſt, that does not ſubject himſelf to an univerſal obedience to all his Laws. To diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, as ſome do, between Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Salvation, and ſay, that Goſpel-works are neceſſary to the Latter, but not to the Former, is to diſtinguiſh where the Scripture makes no difference: For, The Apoſtles ſpeak of a Juſtified perſon, and a ſaved perſon as the <hi>ſame,</hi> and of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification and Salvation as ſo; and they are both promiſcuouſly promiſed to Believing. St. <hi>James</hi> when he is diſcourſing of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, asks this queſtion, <hi>can faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works ſave you?</hi> Where he means the ſame thing as if he had ſaid, <hi>can it juſtifie you?</hi> Nor does it any more derogate from free Grace to make Goſpel-works neceſſary to Juſtification, then it does to ake them nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary to Salvation: For, they are both inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably included each in other: No man can be ſaved that is not Juſtified; for whoſoever is
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64072:65"/>not juſtified at Gods Bar, is <hi>condemned,</hi> and whoever is <hi>juſtified,</hi> is alſo <hi>glorified.</hi> That Text of St. <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 5. duly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, does no way counenance any ſuch Doctrine; for the right underſtanding of which it wil be neceſſary to conſider the whole Context. In the firſt <hi>ver. What ſhall we ſay then</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>that</hi> Abraham <hi>our father</hi> (from whom we derive our ſelves, and who firſt received the Law of Circumciſion, the father of our Perſons, and of our Religion) <hi>as pertaining to the fleſh,</hi> hath found? 'Tis an Interrogation impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Negation, <hi>Abraham</hi> did find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as pertaining to the fleſh. By <hi>fleſh</hi> in Scripture (beſides the Corrupt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) it ſometimes is meant <hi>the ſtrength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural abilities:</hi> So <hi>Iſmael</hi> is ſaid to be born <hi>after the fleſh;</hi> that is, by the meer and ſole efficacy of <hi>nature,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Iſaacs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>according to the ſpirit,</hi> and after the promiſe: And ſometimes by Fleſh is meant the <hi>Legal external privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Jews.</hi> So in the 3d. of the <hi>Philip.</hi> 'tis taken: St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes there, <hi>If any other man thinketh he hath whereof he might truſt in the fleſh; I more: Circumciſed the eighty day,</hi> &amp;c. But 'tis plain what St. <hi>Paul</hi> means here by <hi>fleſh:</hi> For, what
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:64072:66"/>he calls <hi>fleſh</hi> in the firſt <hi>ver.</hi> he calls <hi>works</hi> in the ſecond: <hi>For if</hi> Abraham <hi>were juſtified by works, he hath whereof to glory, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</hi> If <hi>Abraham</hi> were juſtified by the worth and value of his own perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of any works wrought in his own Strength, and by his own Ability, he had whereof to Glory; <hi>But not before God;</hi> which laſt clauſe is a poſitive Negation, and comes in as a <hi>Minor propoſition:</hi> And ſo the the Apoſtles Argument is thus framed, <hi>If</hi> Abraham <hi>were juſtified by works, he had whereof to glory before God;</hi> For 'tis faith on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that excludes glorying before God <hi>(his reward would have been a debt) But he had not whereof to glory before God: Therefore he was not juſtified by works.</hi> And that this is his meaning in thoſe words, <hi>But not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God;</hi> is plain: Becauſe in the next words he applies himſelf in the proof of it: <hi>For, what ſaith the Scripture,</hi> (ſayes he) It does not ſay that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified before God by works, but <hi>Abraham be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved God, and it was accounted to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> God, out of favour and grace, accepted his Faith for Righteouſneſs, which is implyed in the word <hi>Counted,</hi> when: he might juſtly have Refuſed ſo to do <hi>Abraham</hi> could not have <hi>claim'd</hi> it from
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64072:66"/>any <hi>merit</hi> in ſtrict rules of Juſtice <hi>Now to him that worketh</hi> (in the <hi>4th ver.</hi>) <hi>is the reward not reckoned of Grace, but of Debt:</hi> That is, he that hath any thing <hi>due</hi> to his for what he has himſelf in his own ſtrength done, that Reward is a <hi>Debt,</hi> and is not a reward of <hi>Grance:</hi> And ſo if <hi>Abraham</hi> had been a man of ſuch <hi>merits,</hi> had done ſuch works as would in their own nature have juſtified him, and conſtituted him Righteous in the ſight of God, Gods juſtifying him, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging him righteous, had been a <hi>debt due to him:</hi> But <hi>Abraham</hi> was not ſo, he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Sinner,</hi> and could claim no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Debt; And God was pleaſed out of <hi>favour</hi> and grace to Reward <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith and ſuitable obedience, with an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it for Righteouſneſs;</hi> and to juſtifie him thereupon: <hi>But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that juſtifyeth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, his faith is accounted for Righteouſneſs:</hi> That is, Dependeth not upon the ſtrength of his own performances, and ſuch a ſinleſs innocency as will in ſtrict rules of Juſtice acquit him before God, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did not, but Believeth on God that juſtifies the ungodly: That is, a man that has not a Legal ſinleſs perfection, (for, that is meant by the <hi>ungodly</hi>) his Faith is counted for
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:64072:67"/>Righteouſneſs: That is, his Faith through Grace ſhall avail him as much to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and ſtand him in as much ſtead as a perfect ſinleſs Righteouſneſs would do. <hi>Abrahm's</hi> Juſtification was not upon the terms of the Law, or by perfection of Works, (which is inconſiſtent with Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) for he was a great ſinner, and had lived for ſome time in <hi>Heathen Idolatry:</hi> But he was juſtified upon the terms and conditions of another Covenant; that is, upon his <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving God,</hi> and <hi>reforming his Life,</hi> was Pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Accepted: and his Faith and ſincere reformation, though the Grace of another Covenant, was accounted to him for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: Even ſo as the Idolatrous Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles though never circumciſed, may now alſo be juſtified; that is, have their ſins forgiven, if they believe the Goſpel, and Reform their lives: And that by Juſtifying and Imputing Righteouſneſs, is meant the <hi>pardon of ſin,</hi> and that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as an ungodly perſon, by being Pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and not as an Innocent perſon, the next words declare, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>Even as</hi> David <hi>alſo deſcribeth the bleſſedneſs of the man, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom God imputeth Righteouſneſs without works,</hi> (whcih was <hi>Abrahams</hi> caſe) And how is that? Why, <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:64072:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute ſin.</hi> The ſcope of the Apoſtle in this Chapter is to prove, that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was not Juſtified by any original Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, or ſuch a ſinleſs perfection of life, as would make the reward to be of Debt: And ſo not upon the terms of the firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; but he was juſtified by having <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs without Works,</hi> upon the terms of another Covenant. He was juſtified as an ungodly perſon, as a Sinner; That is, was Pardoned upon his ſincere Faith and ſuit able obedience; and ſo arrived at the Bleſſedneſs <hi>David</hi> deſcribes, who takes it for granted, that Bleſſedneſs comes not by unſinning perfect obedience, (which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Pardon) For then he would have ſaid: <hi>Bleſſed are the ſinleſs perfect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that never offended.</hi> But he ſayes, <hi>Bleſſed are they to whom God will not impute ſin, and bleſſed are they whoſe ſins are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</hi> The plain intention of this great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, is by the inſtance of <hi>Abraham</hi> to eſtabliſh Evangelical Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, of which the Gentiles were as capable as the Jews, in oppoſition to Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal: By <hi>works</hi> he intends all along the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>firſt Covenant,</hi> and what was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64072:68"/>to juſtifie a man therein: And by <hi>Faith</hi> he intends the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and all that is conditionally required of us thereby, which is a <hi>ſincere belief</hi> accompanied with <hi>ſuitable obedience.</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> who was juſtified by performing the Goſpel condition, (and not the condition of the Covenant of Works) had ſuch a ſincere Faith accompanied with ſuch obedience, as the <hi>Story</hi> it ſelf, and the Holy Ghoſt by St. <hi>James</hi> poſitively tells us: <hi>His Works wrought with his Faith;</hi> that is, to obtain the ſame End with it, <hi>and by his Works his Faith was perfected.</hi> Tis abſurd to imagine St. <hi>Paul</hi> ever intended to exclude <hi>Goſpel-works,</hi> ſuch a ſincere obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience as is naturally appurtenant to Faith, and is included in it, and ſuppoſed by it, and which is accepted out of meer <hi>Grace,</hi> and cannot pretend to the leaſt <hi>merit:</hi> But he ſpeaks only againſt <hi>ſuch</hi> works as might claim Juſtification as a reward of <hi>Debt,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Grace;</hi> ſuch as the Jews in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on, which would utterly exclude the Gentiles from all poſſibility of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and eſtabliſh it upon a <hi>Legal bottom,</hi> and thereby ſubvert the whole deſign of the Goſpel. By <hi>juſtifying</hi> therefore the <hi>ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> upon <hi>believing,</hi> he means no more then the juſtifying a perſon that has not <hi>ſinleſs
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64072:68"/>legal perfection</hi> (which the firſt Covenant made neceſſary to Juſtification) by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the <hi>condition</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> which condition performed, is through Grace <hi>accepted for Righteouſneſs,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures <hi>actual Pardon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>Has Chriſt ſatisfied for our</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-ſins; <hi>For the breach of</hi> his own Laws <hi>as</hi> Mediator, <hi>or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Queſtion is reſolved by one Text of St. <hi>John,</hi> who tells us, that <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt his ſon cleanſeth from all ſin:</hi> Againſt whatever Law committed, if we perform the Goſpel Condition. Ever ſince the Fall and ſin of man, Chriſt hath been extant in <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> till his full Appearance: And all Pardon and Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs has ſome way or other come through <hi>Him.</hi> He has been the great <hi>medium,</hi> by and through which all <hi>Divine favour</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> has been in all times diſpenſed. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, whoever perform the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> and comes within the compaſs of that Latitude Chriſt by his New Law al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, his ſins of partial unbelief, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſorts of Goſpel-diſobedience, are Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned upon the terms thereof; by the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64072:69"/>tenor of this New Covenant which Chriſt hath purchaſed by his blood, whoſe blood is called <hi>the blood of the Covenant:</hi> By this gracious Covenant a <hi>renewed pardon</hi> is ſtill granted to all <hi>believers</hi> for every ſin at any time committed, upon ſincere <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> and <hi>reformation:</hi> And Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelf to the world upon thoſe <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious terms;</hi> That if they cordially cloſe with him, and receive him as <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> all their paſt ſins ſhall be forgiven: And whenever they ſhall ſin for the future, and come ſhort of that Duty they are to pay to him, upon their <hi>Repentance</hi> they ſhall be <hi>renewed,</hi> and God through and by Him, and for His ſake will exerciſe <hi>continual acts of Pardon</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in all ſuch caſes. And this day of Grace is for ought we know, of the ſame <hi>duration</hi> with every mans <hi>life.</hi> Every man while he <hi>lives</hi> has an <hi>Opportunity</hi> of embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Goſpel: And whoever falls by Temptation and the power of Corruption, after he has ſo done, has yet a <hi>continued poſſibility</hi> while God ſpares him in this world to be reſtored to a Pardoned, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſtate by Repentance. But whoever fails, and comes ſhort in performing the Goſpel-condition; Whoever cloſeth not
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64072:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the Redeemer (who <hi>hath all power put by the father into his hands</hi>) upon his own Terms, not one of that mans ſins will he ever Remit, or Account for to the Father: But is he left to anſwer to that moſt dreadful Charge of the Law; and beſides, by <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting ſo great ſalvation,</hi> falls under the <hi>utmoſt condemnation</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> Is left to God as ſupream Judge of the World in the <hi>higheſt exerciſe of Juſtice,</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the <hi>terms</hi> of his <hi>mercy:</hi> Is left to God without the interpoſition of a <hi>Mediator;</hi> the terrour of which condition the Apoſtle thus expreſſeth: <hi>'Tis a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God:</hi> Where he means <hi>without a Mediator.</hi> For 'tis ſpoken <hi>in terrorem</hi> to the Converted <hi>Jews,</hi> who were in great danger of Apoſtatizing from the Goſpel, and the faith of the Mediator, and returning back to the old Cancelled diſpenſation of the Law, <hi>the end of which was Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this whole matter. The <hi>making</hi> and <hi>redeeming</hi> of a man is original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founded in an <hi>eternal tranſaction</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>Trinity.</hi> God ſaw it fit to Create man at the firſt with a <hi>mutable Will,</hi> with an inherent <hi>freedom</hi> of <hi>choice;</hi> though he perfectly knew and foreſaw all the <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents,</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:64072:70"/>and what <hi>uſe</hi> man would make of it. The <hi>Reaſon</hi> of this is not to be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired</hi> into: For although God is pleaſed in Scripture to permit us to Treat with him about his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and to Diſcourſe with us about the <hi>equity</hi> of his <hi>proceedings, whether his wayes be not equal</hi> towards us, and <hi>ours unequal</hi> towards Him: Yet he never admits us to any conference with him about his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> never ſuffers any humane inquiry to be made Whether he does <hi>Wiſely</hi> or no in what he does, but ſtill puts us to ſilence in that point with his abſolute <hi>Soveraignty over us,</hi> and brands that man with a <hi>Wo that ſo ſtrives with his Maker,</hi> and ſhall dare to ſay, <hi>Why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> Whatever God does, we have theſe two prevailing Reaſons to Acquieſce in it, Firſt, That 'tis done by him that has the ſupream Right of <hi>diſpoſing All:</hi> He that <hi>made</hi> all, is ſitteſt to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> all, and muſt needs be beſt intituled ſo to do. Secondly, That 'tis the reſult of <hi>infinite Attributes,</hi> ſuch wherein is inherent the utmoſt poſſible Perfection we are able to conceive of in every kind. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever oppoſeth, or queſtioneth <hi>ſuch Wiſd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om,</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>higheſt Folly.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever oppoſeth or thwarteth <hi>ſuch Juſtice</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>greateſt Injuſtice;</hi> and ſo
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64072:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>in all other inſtances. God, in this caſe, ſaw it beſt to make man <hi>Free,</hi> and leave him to the utmoſt <hi>exerciſe</hi> of that <hi>freedom,</hi> that ſo Man might appear to be what he <hi>would be,</hi> and God might appear to be what his <hi>is.</hi> Evil had never been but that 'twas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely <hi>better</hi> it <hi>ſhould be</hi> then <hi>not to be:</hi> For when the Creature has ſinn'd to the utmoſt, God over-rules that ſin to <hi>excellent Ends;</hi> and from the depths of Divine Wiſdom we ſee it ſo brought about, that <hi>glorious effects</hi> reſult from it: Though the <hi>commiſſion</hi> of ſin is no way <hi>excuſed</hi> thereby, and the <hi>guilt</hi> of it reſts at every mans <hi>own door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From created <hi>freedom</hi> all <hi>ſin</hi> and all <hi>miſery</hi> the adjunct of it had their firſt <hi>riſe,</hi> and from thence they were originally <hi>produced.</hi> This created freedom of will, was in it ſelf and its own nature, as firſt fram'd, <hi>excellent,</hi> and a bright beam of Divine perfection, being of a Noble Faculty capable of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual choice of what was beſt; and 'tis far more excellent <hi>freely</hi> to <hi>chooſe</hi> what is ſo, then from any outward <hi>neceſſity</hi> to become <hi>obliged</hi> to it. It was alſo ſuited in its nature to Gods giving a Law, and mans Obedience: Of the fitneſs of which we may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, when we reflect upon that Relation there is between the <hi>Creator</hi> and a <hi>Creature,</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:64072:71"/>from this Root of created freedom ſo ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate an adjunct to ſo noble a creature as Man, and in its right exerciſe alwayes cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in God as the ſupream and chiefeſt good, and moſt proper object of choice. From hence ſprang up the <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>apoſtacy</hi> of humane nature: For no man can, or from the beginning could ſay when he is tempted: <hi>I am tempted of God; for God cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth he any man: But every man is tempted when he is led aſide of his own luſt, and enticed.</hi> This <hi>freedom</hi> in man declining to <hi>diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> puts a period to all his <hi>happineſs,</hi> Diſorders, and Disjoynt's all his Faculties, and ſtraight way renders him obnoxious to that ſupream and dreadful Attribute of his Maker, his <hi>Juſtice.</hi> God upon the firſt declenſion of this freedom, upon mans firſt diſobedience, inflicts the utmoſt penalty of his Law: Nor can we ſuppoſe it otherwiſe, but that God in the firſt inſtance of that kind, would give his Creatures to know what <hi>ſin was!</hi> That a Rebellion againſt Him the Higheſt, moſt Abſolute, and moſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Being, was of all things the moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, contain'd in its bowels the utmoſt Evil, being an oppoſition to the Greateſt Good, and muſt needs expoſe to the Worſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:64072:71"/>of Conditions: For nothing can <hi>oppoſe God,</hi> and be <hi>happy,</hi> or <hi>proſper.</hi> Nor would it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt either with the Juſtice, or Wiſdom of ſuch a Soveraign as God is, to give Laws, but upon the moſt perfect and unalterable Reaſon, and upon that account, to adhere to their punctual Execution: And of this we are ſufficiently <hi>informed,</hi> when we ſee that nothing leſs then a ſatisfaction made by the Death of our Saviour, (that ſtupendious and Miraculous expedient of Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, beyond the ken of Angels or Men, whereby God receives a redundancy of compenſation) could relieve or releaſe us from the ſeverity and ſtrict execution of the Law of Works, and introduce that <hi>better Covenant, the Law of Grace,</hi> by which we are now juſtified and ſaved. We muſt not imagine God <hi>dallyes</hi> when he gives Laws to the world, or that he will connive at the breach of them, or <hi>repeal</hi> them as men do; 'Tis other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with the ſupream Law-giver and Judge of all the earth, to whom all things that are to come, are fully and certainly known, and before whom all future events are ever preſent.</p>
            <p>Man, by this choſen diſobedience to the Law of his Maker, ſtands before him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64072:72"/>by as an object of his Juſtice, who being alſo <hi>eſſentially good, gracious</hi> and <hi>forgiving,</hi> and acting nothing but in a perfect comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with himſelf, thoſe two Attributes of <hi>Mercy</hi> and Juſtice (So far as we are able to reach) remain in ſuch a juncture utterly <hi>irreconcilable,</hi> till by a Miracle of Divine Wiſdom (which can never be ſufficiently ador'd) a way is found out to make thoſe two Contending Attributes both <hi>trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant: Juſtice</hi> is fully <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> brought into its <hi>utmoſt exerciſe,</hi> and all the Flood-gates of Divine Goodneſs let open upon the world: This is all effected by the glorious and gracious undertaking of our bleſſed Redeemer; by whom <hi>life and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality is brought to light,</hi> our Salvation proclaimed, and ſtands for ever eſtabliſhed upon theſe three fundamental points. Firſt, That Chriſt perfectly performed all that was neceſſary for him to perform, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute him a ſufficient Mediator between God and Man, exactly fulfilled all the Law of his publick Mediatorſhip, and was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of God ſo to have done: A ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inſtance whereof he gave to the world in <hi>raiſing him from the dead, and exalting him at his own right hand.</hi> Secondly, That by reaſon of the Dignity of Chriſts <hi>perſon,</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:64072:72"/>his obedience and ſufferings were infinitely of more intrinſick <hi>value</hi> and <hi>weight</hi> then all the obedience and ſufferings of Mankind ever were, or poſſibly could be; and ſo they are accounted of before God. Thirdly, That being perform'd in our Nature, and wholly upon our Account, God by an infinitely gracious Statute in Heaven accepts them <hi>for us</hi> (though not as done <hi>by us</hi>) and reckons all the <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>advantages</hi> of them by way of <hi>imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Chriſt having made ſuch a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to God for the ſins of the world, and thereby reverſed that ſentence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation that by the Law was Recorded againſt us, has as Mediator the power of diſpenſing Pardon wholly committed to Him. For, <hi>the Father</hi> now <hi>judges no man, but has committed all judgment unto the Son.</hi> That is, Chriſt as Mediator is eſtabliſhed <hi>King.</hi> And the world is now to be judged by a Law of Grace: And two things in the exerciſe of this Mediatory Dominion are Eternally ſtipulated between the Father and the Son. Firſt, that all pardon and Forgiveneſs ſhall be diſpenſed upon ſuch <hi>Conditions;</hi> that is, upon the <hi>terms</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by the Goſpel, whereby the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:64072:73"/>of all the Divine Attributes, as well as of Mercy and Forgiveneſs, is highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play'd. And Secondly, That that power, Chriſt as Mediator is veſted withall, to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power</hi> and <hi>inable</hi> whom he pleaſeth, by the ſending forth of the Holy Ghoſt, to <hi>perform the Goſpel-Condition,</hi> ſhall be exerted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thoſe alone to whom God in his Eternal Counſels (who had all things in proſpect and fore-knowledge, and the whole of all mens circumſtances before him from Everlaſting) deſigned preſent Grace, and future Glory.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who through Divine Grace and Aſſiſtance receive Chriſt as he propounds himſelf to us in the Goſpel, are by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thereof <hi>juſtified</hi> before God: And he ſo propounds himſelf, that whoever Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives him, is thereby obliged to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of <hi>all Goſpel-Righteouſneſs:</hi> And when the whole of Chriſts undertaking <hi>to bring many ſons to glory</hi> ſhall be perfected and compleated, we ſhall then ſee that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle calls it, that <hi>multiform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſapientia Dei, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold wiſdom of God</hi> in curious variety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about this matter, and the glorious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency there is in a Sinners Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in its <hi>contrivance,</hi> in its <hi>procuring cauſe,</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:64072:73"/>in its <hi>condition,</hi> and in its <hi>final effect;</hi> And thence will reſult Everlaſting <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Hymns</hi> of <hi>praiſe and thanksgiving to him that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
